<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Discourse of eternitie, collected and composed for the common good being necessary for all seasons, but especially for this time of calamitie and destruction.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36093</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14406</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11844808</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11844808</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49814</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36093)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49814)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 26:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Discourse of eternitie, collected and composed for the common good being necessary for all seasons, but especially for this time of calamitie and destruction.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By George Miller, for Christopher Meredith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eternity.</term>
               <term>Future life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49814:1"/>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:49814:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A DISCOVRSE OF ETERNITIE, Collected and Compoſed for the Common good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being neceſſary for all ſeaſons, but eſpecially for this time of cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and deſtruction.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The ſinners in Zion are afraid, a fear is come upon the Hypocrites: who amongſt us ſhall dwell with the devouring fire? who amongſt us ſhall dwel with the everlaſting burnings?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſay. 33.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>He that beleeveth in the Son, hath everlaſting life, and he that obeyeth not the Son, ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ioh. 3.36.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>George Miller,</hi> for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith,</hi> at the ſigne of the Crane in <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49814:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49814:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any man would know the Patron of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, let him under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that it belongs to <hi>Every body.</hi> For there is not a man under heaven, be he <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Subject, Noble</hi> or <hi>Ignoble, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barian, Scythian, Bond</hi> or <hi>Free,</hi> but lives unavoidably under the law of <hi>Death,</hi> and within the <hi>Pale</hi> of <hi>Eternity.</hi> Now as all men are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inrolled into this book of <hi>Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> ſo muſt they of conſequence be equally intereſſed in this diſcourſe. Therefore I commend theſe ſhort Meditations of a long <hi>Eternity</hi> for the favour of protection (as in right they appertain) to <hi>Every body.</hi> But will every one counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb facs="tcp:49814:3"/>them with a friendly welcom? Certainly, ſuch entertainment may rather be wiſht then hoped for. This <hi>Eternitie</hi> (whereof I treat) findes, for the moſt part, but ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der countenance, and cold reſpect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſons of men. For where is the man of ſo ſetled and well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed temper, that can fix and termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate his thoughts upon that <hi>everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtate</hi> which abides him in the life to come? That can orderly frame, &amp; readily diſpoſe his heart to ſearch into it, and his tongue to diſcourſe of it, and his will to affect it? I doubt not but flaſhes of Eternitie, and tranſient thoughts thereof doe often ſwim in the brain, and ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle about the heart of a ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all worldling; but there they lodge not, they take not up their reſt. The covetous man ſoon ſtrangles them in his money bagges, the drunkard drowns them in his fulcups, the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb facs="tcp:49814:3"/>ſwallows them with his dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſuperfluous fare, every man in his way ſtrives to keep that from his heart here, which he cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly deliver his ſoul from hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, his endleſse Eternity. Thus are we unhappily ingenious to deceive our ſelves, wittie to invent new waies, to put off the melancholy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the evil day. We plod daily onward towards our long home, but we think not of any rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konings till we come to our journeyes end: we fear not the pit, till we be ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recoverably plunged into it, we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know the true worth of time, nor price to the deſert, our golden hours, untill they be <hi>everlaſtingly</hi> loſt and gone; and then, alas, thoſe precious dayes which we have prodigally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended in the luſts of our fleſh, and vanity of our eye, we ſhall infinitely deſire to redeem, (were it poſsible) even with tears of blood. Oh then
<pb facs="tcp:49814:4"/>whoſoever thou art, examine with due care the ſtate of thy ſoul: if thy luſt be thy life, and thy ſenſuality thy joy, then gull not thy ſoul with hope of pardon. Imagine not to finde two heavens, one upon earth, another above it, aſſure thy ſelf, though thou make with the Eagle thy neſt on high, and ſeat thy habitation as it were in the clouds, yet thy highneſſe will not free thee from the ſtroak of death, nor deliver thy ſoul from the nethermoſt hell. Now if there be any man ſo unmercifull to his ſoul, that (notwithſtanding all that is, or ſhall be ſaid) will deſperately on in his curſed way; I ſay no more but this, He that is filthy, let him be filthy ſtill. The ſmart of this <hi>Eternity</hi> they that will not beleeve ſhall feel.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:49814:4"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Contents of the firſt Book.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> Containing an Introduction to the enſuing diſcourſe.</item>
               <item n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Containing a diſcription of <hi>Eternity,</hi> with a brief declaration of the nature and condition of it.</item>
               <item n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Expreſſing how all men doe naturally beleeve this <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Explaining how nature hath repreſented and ſhadowed out <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> to us in ſome of the <hi>Creatures.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Containing a ſhort digreſſion, touching the <hi>Eternity</hi> of the damned.</item>
               <item n="6">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Wherein the question is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Wherefore a finite ſinne is recompenſed with an infinite pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment?</hi> Wherein alſo is further ſhewed, that the <hi>Severity of Gods Juſtice</hi> therein, doth no way dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the greatneſſe of his <hi>Mercy.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:49814:5"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Contents of the ſecond Book.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> Containing an Exhortation to <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> grounded upon the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Shewing that there is no other way, nor poſſible means to attain to the true <hi>Eternity,</hi> but by a confident affiance upon the <hi>Mercy</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Certain concluſions drawn from the ſerious and devout conſideration of <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Directions for the better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of our lives in the way to a happy <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <p>By the word <hi>procure</hi> p. <hi>76.</hi> l. <hi>22.</hi> I re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate to a reward of grace, not of debt.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49814:5"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE FIRST CHAPTER,</hi> Containing an Introduction to the enſuing Diſcourſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Feciſti nos ad te, domine, &amp; inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etum eſt cor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcat in te. <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Conf. cap.</hi> 1.</note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing can fully ſatisfie the minde of Man but that which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove man: all the treaſures and riches under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven cannot make up a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable object for the ſoul. For that which muſt terminate the deſires of ſo excellent and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine a nature, muſt bee of a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent and like condition with it, that is, infinite and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall. Now no ſublunary bleſſings extend thus farre: All
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49814:6"/>worldly happineſſe, and earthly delights have their changes, and have their death. They are ſhort in their continuance, and uncomfortable in their end. For they leave us, when we leave the world, and they nothing availe us in the day of triall, when our bodies ſhall deſcend into the ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie valley, and our ſouls returne to God that gave them, then all the choiceſt comforts of this life glide away from us as the ſtream, and the ſunne of our joy will ſet for ever. Our beautie, wherein we have ſo much prided our ſelves, ſhall turne into rottennes, our mirth into wormewood, our glory into duſt. Now if this be the condition, if ſuch the ſtate of our beſt pleaſing contentations here below, how undiſcreetly improvident of our ſoules wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare ſhould we be, to bound ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49814:6"/>affections on the things of this world? what a madneſſe beyond admiration, were it in us, to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle out our time, to waſte and weare out our moſt precious daies in the vanities under the funne, as if God had placed us here on earth, like the Leviathan in the Sea, to take our paſtime in it, to ingulfe our ſoules into the ſenſuall pleaſures of this life, as if we had neither hope nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a life to come? what an intolerable ſtupiditie were it, for the ſhort fruition of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary content here, to plunge our ſelves for everlaſtingnes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſea, as it were, of fire and brimſtone, where we ſhall ſee no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ankes, and feele no bottome? Me thinks the ſerious conſidera, ſon hereof, ſhould even cut the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eart, and damp the mirth, and wound the very ſoul of the moſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49814:7"/>glorious and ſelfe pleaſing worldling, whoſe life is nothing but a change of recreations, to think upon his fading ſtate, his flowing condition, his decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning joy, his dying life, and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe eternitie, to ſee how all things in him, and about him goe ſpeedily forward in a moſt ſenſible declination, to behold with his eyes, how his goods, and his greatneſſe, his livings, and his life, and all the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious delights which his ſenſuall heart enjoyes, are already wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as it were for their flight, and muſt ſhortly bid him an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing farewell. And then what ſhall be his ſtay, where ſhall be his ſhelter, what will remain to be done, but with that ſad and diſconſolate Heathen, to ſhut up all in that hopeleſſe and helpleſſe lamentation, <hi>Anxius vixi, dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49814:7"/>morior, heu, quo vado?</hi> I have ſquandered out my life in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull way, I have lived unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvedly, and die doubtfully, and now whither away O my ſoul? woe is the and alas for evermore. And ſuch is the bitter cloſe, and uncomfortable end of all thoſe who goe deſperately on in the waies of their hearts, and in the ſight of their eyes, and make not God their ſtrength; though their excellency mount up to the Heavens (ſaith <hi>Job</hi>) and their heads reach unto the cloudes, yet ſhall they periſh for ever as their dung, and the eye which hath ſeen them ſhall doe ſo no more, <hi>Job.</hi> 20.6. O then how deeply doth it concerne us, to raiſe up our deſires to things above, to ſix our hearts upon the true rock, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o drawe our waters of comfort from the everliving fountain, to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49814:8"/>truſt ſo much more on God, by how much we have leſſe on earth to truſt to. Now for our better incouragement to this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to the end we may the more eaſily unlooſe our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the imbracements of this world, it will not be unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy our labour to meditate a while upon the nature of that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie which doth unavoidably abide for us either in horror or happineſſe in the life to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Containing a deſcription of Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with a brief declaration of the nature and condition of it.</head>
                  <p>ETernitie is an infinite, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, bottomeleſſe gulfe, which no line can faddome, no time can reach, no age can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49814:8"/>to, no tongue can expreſſe. It is a duration alwaies preſent, a being alwaies in being, it is one perpetuall day, which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee an Evening. Infinite are the deſcriptions of the Ancients, and divers their expreſſions, touching this Eternitie. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> conceiving that God was eternall, and his duration and being to be properly term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Eternitie, repreſented the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine power by a Circle, which had neither beginning nor end. And hence it was that the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Romans erected Temples, which they dedicated to their Gods in a circular figure. Thus <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> devoted a round Temple to the Majeſtie of <hi>Veſta.</hi> And <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> the like in honour of all the Gods. <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor as</hi> the better to expreſſe that God was eternall, commanded
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49814:9"/>his Scholars that ſo oft as they accommodated themſelves to the worſhip of God, they ſhould turne themſelves round. The Turkes every morning aſcend into an high Tower built in the faſhion of the <hi>Egyptian Pyrami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> where they devoutly ſalute their God and Mahomet, crying with a lowd and roaring voice, <hi>Deus ſemper fuit, ſemper<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> erit,</hi> God alwaies hath been, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will be. <hi>Mercurius Triſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistus,</hi> the moſt famous among the Philoſophers, repreſented God the true Eternity by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall ſphear, whoſe Center was every where, but without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny circumference, becauſe he was the beginning and end of all things, not bounded within any compaſſe, nor terminated in any limits. It was an uſuall cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome among the <hi>Naſomons,</hi> an
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49814:9"/>ancient people in <hi>Africa,</hi> that they coveted to dye ſitting, and would alway be buried in the ſame poſture, ſitting in Cells un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath the earth, and this they did to ſignify by that unmovea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble geſture, that they ſhould now ſing a <hi>requiem</hi> from the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of this troubleſome world, and had now arrived at the haven of eternall quietneſſe. Thus we ſee how theſe miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble heathen, who had no other light but nature, no other guide but thoſe lame and corrupted principles, which were left in them after the fall, did notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, according to their broken and weak apprehenſions, tire out themſelves in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Eternity, and how ever they were unhappily igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in the wayes of God in this life, yet they earneſtly laboured
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49814:10"/>to know what ſhould become of themſelves hereafter, and to finde out the ſtate of the life to come: Oh how juſtly might I (were it not a digreſſion!) take up a lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and deplore the wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed condition of our times, how ſhort doe we fall, even of the perfection of Heathens? how few are there in compariſon of the generallity of people, that caſt forth ſo much as a thought upon Eternity? we live here as if there were no life hereafter. Our Earth is our Heaven, and our pleaſures our Paradiſe, we crown our heads with roſe buds, we eat of the fat, and drinke of the ſweet, and ſay in our hearts, no evil ſhall happen to us, and yet when we have done all, <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes humanae conſolationes ſunt deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationes,</hi> Hearts eaſe will not growe in this earthly garden, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49814:10"/>true reſt will not be found, but in the true place, the eternall Hieruſalem, ſound and entire contentment hath no rooting in this world. For as one hath it excellently,<note n="*" place="margin">Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum tuum velle &amp; videre, &amp; non inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, niſi ſemper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquid pati debere, aut ſponte aut invite, &amp; ita crucem ſem per in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venies.</note> Diſpoſe and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall all things to thine own hearts deſire, yet ſhalt thou (doe what thou canſt) ſtill meet with ſome croſſe or preſſure in the way. Since it is ſo, let us not then determinate our affections in theſe earthly things, which are of no continuance, but let us ſend our hearts before us to thoſe heavenly manſions, where they ſhall be crowned with fulneſſe of happineſſe, and ſhall ſwimme in ſtreams of pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Certainely there is no true reſt but that which is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and the ſweeteſt refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our ſouls can finde in this world, conſiſts in the ſerious
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49814:11"/>meditation of the joyes to come, in devoting our ſelves and all we have to his ſervice, from whom we have them, in truſting to him, and relying on him. For out of God the ſoul findes no reſting place to ſet her foot on, but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where ſtorms and waves, death and hell abide her: when we have improved our content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the very height of our deſires, when we have attained as much happineſſe as the world can give us, yet then may we be cut off perchance in the midſt of our dayes, when our breaſts are full of milk, and our bones full of marrow: or ſuppoſe we ſpinne the threed of our life to a longer day, and God crown us here with the bleſſings of his left hand, the comforts of this life, and length of years, yea though all things favour our longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49814:11"/>in this world, yet in the end time and age will ruine us. We ſhall bring our years to an end, like a tale that is told, and ſhall vaniſh away like a ſhadow. Though we live many years, and in them all we rejoice, yet in the end we ſhall remember the daies of darkneſſe, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> and the time ſhall come that the eye which ſaw us, ſhall ſee us no more.<note n="*" place="margin">Soles occidere &amp; redire poſſunt, nobis cum occidet ſemel bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis lux, nox eſt perpetuò una dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mienda. <hi>Cat.</hi>
                     </note> The ſunne ſets, and riſeth again, but we alas, when our glaſſe is runne, and the ſhort gleam of our ſummers day is ſpent, ſhall never return till our laſt ſummons, when the dead ſhall hear the voice of the Sonne of God, and they that heare it ſhall live, and come forth of their graves, they that have done good to the reſurrection of life, and they that have done evil, to the reſurrection of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49814:12"/>both to Eternity, and then ſhall follow that large day, that ſhall never ſhut in, that infinite continuation of time that ſhall never end, that unlimited Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which ever hath been, and is, and will be the ſame for ever, when the Sunne ſhall no more yeeld her light by day, nor the Moon her brightneſſe by night, but God ſhall be our light, and the Lord our glory. But oh the unhappy condition of our age, who is there that ponders theſe things with a digeſted me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, that looks into the ſtate of his ſoul with a ſerious eye, and conſidereth his wayes? That endeavours to lay a good foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for the time to come? we ſtand at the door of Eternity, and while we live, we are every day entring into it, its but a ſtroak of death, and we are gon, even in a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49814:12"/>moment, and whither? from our ſhort and fading delights, to an endleſſe, eaſeleſſe gulfe, where our worme ſhall never die, nor our fire ſhall never out. Now let all thoſe who ſwim in the ſtreams of their voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, putting far from them the evil day, who labour to expell from their hearts, and to ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle in the bud the ſad conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of their approaching infelicities, let them (I ſay) know, that they may fall into this vaſt gulf of Eternity, when they leaſt ſuſpect it; into which, when once they have unhappily plunged themſelves, they may deſire redemption, but ſhall not finde it.<note n="*" place="margin">Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam iſtinc ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, nullus poeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae locus, nullus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus <hi>Cyp,</hi>
                     </note> It ſhall be one of their torments, to know they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be out of torment. All the gold of <hi>Ophir</hi> cannot purchaſe them one minute of relief from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49814:13"/>their unexpreſſible miſeries. But now, even now is the jubile, now is the accepted time, now is the promulgation of pardon, there remains nothing for our parts, but to ſue it forth: we need not many hundred of years or num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of dayes to redeem our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent time, and to waſh out our contracted pollutions, no, one day will, through Gods gracious favour, and loving indulgence, procure more mercy here, then Eternity of time can obtain here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, one ſigh from a true ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull heart here, ſhall prevail to diſcharge more debts, then infinite ages ſhall acquit or ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie for hereafter. Here God with patience expects our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but if we abuſe his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, and come not in, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after with trembling we ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide his judgement,</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49814:13"/>
                  <p>Let us therefore be wiſe in time, &amp; remember our Creatour in the dayes of our youth, before the evil daies come, and the years approach, wherein we ſhall ſay, we have no pleaſure in them, before our duſt returne into the wombe from whence it came, and our lungs be locked up into the breathles earth, before that black and gloomy day, the day of death and diſſolution appeare to us, the which (if our timely repentance here prevent not our doom) will ſeal up our ſouls to eternall darkneſſe. Let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that whereſoever we are, whatſoever we goe about,<note place="margin">Immani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia autem manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans, per omnia ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paret &amp; in om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> we ſtand every minute of our time in the glorious preſence of an * incomprehenſible majeſtie, whoſe bright and moſt piercing eye, is ten thouſand times clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then the Sunne, who knows
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49814:14"/>all hearts, ſees all actions, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands all counſells, views all perſons, there's not a word in the tongue, not a thought in the heart, not a ſpark of luſt in the fleſh, though never ſo ſoftly blown, and ſecretly kindled, but he beholds it altogether, he is all ear to hear, all hand to puniſh, and when and where he pleaſe, all power to protect, and all grace to pardon, he that findes not his mercy, ſhall feel his fury: and who amongſt us can dwell with devouring fire? who amongſt us can dwell with everlaſting burnings?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49814:14"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Expreſsing how all men doe natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally beleeve this Eternity.</head>
                  <p>VVIthin theſe hundred years many nations have been diſcovered, and many are diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered ſtill, which were unfound in former ages. Amongſt them ſome have been found to live without law, without King, but yet none without ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and of ſome ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting being in the world to come. What moved the <hi>Brack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> in <hi>India,</hi> and the <hi>Magies</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> to begin and end their undertakings with prayers to God? What moved <hi>Publius Scipio</hi> never to enter into the Senate houſe before he had aſcended the <hi>Capitol,</hi> avowing that principle as conſtantly in his practice, as he did in his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49814:15"/>
                     <hi>A Jove principium?</hi> What made <hi>Caligula</hi> (which threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the aire if it rained on his game-plaies) yet, to runne under his bed, and wrapp his cap about his head at a clap of thunder? What moved <hi>Attillius Regulus</hi> (who had no other teacher then a naturall illumination) to preferre the obligation of his oath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſafety of his life, and rather then he would break his ingaged word and promiſe to the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> expoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to all the torments that the cruelty and malice of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies could inflict upon him? What moved the <hi>Saguntines,</hi> a people of <hi>Arragon,</hi> to that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted reſolution of theirs, who having plighted their faith and loyalty by ſolemn oath to the <hi>Romans,</hi> choſe rather to entomb
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49814:15"/>themſelves voluntarily in a fire, which they made in their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place, then to break their faith to the ſaid <hi>Romans,</hi> which they had ſo ſolemnly ſwore and ſacredly avowed under their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection? what, I ſay, could move theſe meer naturaliſts to ſuch a fear of an oath, to ſuch a trembling at Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to ſuch auſterity, and care, and cenſorious circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection in all their waies and actions, but that they natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally apprehended what they truly and diſtinctly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not, <hi>viz.</hi> Some im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall happineſſe and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting being? and this they conceived was beyond the mountaines, or above them, or in ſome other world, they knew not where, according as their ſeverall fancies led them.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49814:16"/>
                  <p>Certainly they would never have ſo much undervalued their earthly contentments, and ſold all the comforts of this life (as ſome of them did) at ſo cheap a rate, but that they truſted to ſome future reſt of more endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſubſtance after this life, and comfortably expected the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall fruition of ſuch joyes as ſhould abundantly countervaile the loſſe of all their pleaſures. When I revolve in my minde the <hi>Stoicall</hi> reſervedneſſe, the moderation, the unconquerable courage of theſe miſerable <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> when I ſee <hi>Cleombrotus</hi> in hope of immortality to tumble himſelf voluntarily down a hill, when I ſee <hi>Socrates</hi> ſmile upon his hemlock, and ſullen <hi>Scevola</hi> burn off his own hand without ever gnaſhing his teeth at it, when I ſee <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> ſcorn his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49814:16"/>own life, becauſe his enemy gave it him, and tear off the ſalve from his bleeding ſides, which his own ſword had peirced: When I thus behold theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy ſouls in the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to conquer nature it ſelf, and to build theſe their reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon no other ground, but the ſlender hope of ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known contentment in the life to come, me thinks theſe mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous acts of theirs, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are not for the imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of us <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> yet doe they tend to our condemnation. Their hope did exceed their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and our knowledge doth exceed our practcie. God hath revealed to us the immortality of the ſoul, and the eternity to come, in a farre more clear and perſpicuous manner, then ever to the heathen Idolaters, and yet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49814:17"/>we leſſe regard it: what ſhould more affect us here, ſince our li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e is but a vapour, then to know what ſhall become of us hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? and yet the conſideration hereof lyes like a weight of lead upon our ſouls; and we judge the very thought hereof a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. We readily apprehend ſuch things as concerne us in this world: our honours, our preferments, our pleaſures we look on with a cheerfull eye: but alas, with how ſlow and dull a pace doe we proceed in the purſuit of our future bleſſednes? we meet with many ſtops in our way, many turnings in our jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: and the truth is, we muſt not expect to arrive at ſo happy a haven without ſome ſtorms; but what are theſe to Eternity, that long day that ſhall never ſhut in; that <hi>unum perpetuum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49814:17"/>that beginning ever in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, in which the bleſſed doe everlaſtingly enjoy their happineſſe, and renew their pleaſures, and the damned are alwaies dying, and yet never dye? O that the meditation of this our future ſtate could ſinke deep enough into our hearts, that we would make that the object of our thoughts here, which muſt be the object of our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts hereafter, that the ſenſe of our ſinnes were the chief mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our ſorrowes, then ſhould we enjoy an eternity hereafter, boundleſſe for time, endleſſe for happineſſe, where our joyes ſhould be ſuch, as ſhould nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther change nor periſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49814:18"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Explaining how Nature hath repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and ſhadowed out Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to us in ſome of the creatures.</head>
                  <p>NOw to the end we ſhould be the farther encouraged un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the inquiſition of eternity, God hath not only planted the knowledge hereof in the hearts of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> but hath alſo repreſented it in the nature of the creatures. For if we ſearch with a narrow eye into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of nature, how many things ſhall we finde in the world, as lively reſemblances, ſhadowing as it were, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing out unto us this eternity? <hi>Solinus</hi> reports of a ſtone in <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadia,</hi> which being once infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med burnes perpetually. And
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49814:18"/>of this matter or the like, were your burning lamps made, which continued (as <hi>Hiſtories</hi> ſpeak) ſo many hundred years in ancient Sepulchres. Like here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, in the nature of it, is your <hi>Linum vivum,</hi> a certain kinde of linen known in <hi>India,</hi> which is uncombuſtible, nay, it is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not conſumed by the fire, but it is as it were cleanſed, and waſhed, and purified by the heat thereof; and hence it was that the bodies of the ancient <hi>Roman Emperors,</hi> when they were to be buried according to the funerall rites of thoſe times, were ſhroud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up into ſuch linen, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their aſhes and to avoid a confuſion and mixture of their bodies with common duſt.</p>
                  <p>Behold, here nature it ſelf ſuggeſts an eternity to thy ſoul, while it preſents to thee ſuch
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49814:19"/>things as the fire cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, many other ſuch <hi>Symboles</hi> and repreſentations of immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity may be found in the book of the creatures. The <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> liveth in the fire, and periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not. Thoſe famous hills in <hi>Sicily</hi> have been on fire continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, beyond the memory of man, and yet remain whole and unconſumed. The like we reade of that <hi>Oleum incombuſtibile,</hi> (as <hi>Historians</hi> call it) an oyle that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver burns, but will never waſte; and of the matter of this was that burning torch compoſed, which was found in <hi>Tulliola,</hi> daughter of <hi>Cicero</hi> her ſepulchre: which (as ſtory ſpeaks) continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed burning fifteen hundred years. Theſe and many other ſhadowes and traces of eternity <hi>God</hi> hath vouchſafed us, to ſtirre up our dead and drouſy hearts,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49814:19"/>to a more exact inquiſition, and ſerious conſideration of the time to come: For in the book of the creature, we may ſee the power of the <hi>Creatour,</hi> and out of theſe particular works of his, we may underſtand that, that <hi>God</hi> which hath endowed nature with ſuch admirable qualities, can give the fleſh alſo ſuch a condition, that it ſhall endure, according to his wiſe diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, either torments, or happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for evermore.</p>
                  <p>Now then, to draw all this to an iſſue, ſince it is undoubtedly true, that <hi>God</hi> hath provided an everlaſting being, for the ſouls of men in the world to come: ſince he hath engraven the knowledge hereof, as with an iron pen in the conſciences of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> ſince he hath given us ſo many lively reſemblances, and traces
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49814:20"/>thereof in the ſecrets of nature, and in the works of his creation. Oh how ſhould the meditation of this take up our deepeſt thoughts, our refineſt affections? how ſhould this cauſe us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon our ſouls; to ponder our waies, and with an imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all eie look into our own eſtates, and ſeriouſly conſider with our ſelves, whether are we in the number of thoſe that are become Kings and Prieſts unto God, and have our hearts inlightned with the ſupernaturall life of grace and godlineſſe, or lye we yet polluted in our own blood?</p>
                  <p>Oh, how can man be at reſt and quiet in his minde, till he be aſſured and ſecured in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, ſince that upon it depends his everlaſting eſtate in another world? our daies we ſee are woven with a ſlender threed, our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49814:20"/>time ſhort, our end uncertain, and when the oyl in our lamps is ſpent, and our glaſſe runne out, then we flee in a moment to an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting being,<note place="margin">Ex unico momento pendet du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas.</note> either in horror or happineſſe, where we ſhall receive according to the works of our hands. If we have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved our ſelves ſincere in <hi>Gods</hi> ſervice, juſt in our actions, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in our callings, faithfull in our promiſes: we ſhall then at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the end of our faith, the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our ſouls: and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of our well ſpent life, ſhal at that diſmall day repleniſh our ſouls with abundance of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; Then all our tears ſhall be wiped from our eys; what we have ſowed in ſorrow, we ſhall reap in joy, when we have finiſhed our courſe, and ended our combate with ſinne and death: then ſhall our crown be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49814:21"/>ſure, our victory glorious, and our triumph <hi>Eternall;</hi> our grave ſhall be but as a ſweet refreſhing place to our wearied bodies, and death ſhall be our day-ſtarre, to everlaſting brightneſſe.</p>
                  <p>But on the other ſide; if we have in the whole courſe of our warfare here, expended our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious time in the ſervice of ſinne and Satan, and crumbled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the beſt and choiceſt of our years in the deſires of the fleſh, and ſports of vanity; if our luſts have been our law, and we have traded in pleaſure all our dayes, then heare our dreadfull doom: Our mirth will be turned into wormwood, and our joy into heavines: all our delights in this earth ſhall vaniſh as the flower, our ſun ſhall ſet in a cloud, and our daies of jollity and contentation ſhall irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49814:21"/>be involved and turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to perpetuall darkneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Containing a ſhort digreſsion touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the eternity of the damned.</head>
                  <p>ANd here it will not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable, nor any digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the point in hand, to conſider with our ſelves, for our better encouragement to the wayes of holineſſe, the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that eternity which the damned have in Hell. O the unhappy and ever deplorable ſtate of thoſe poor ſouls, who feel nothing for the preſent, but wrath and vengeance, and can expect nothing to come, but the vialls of <hi>Gods</hi> indignation to be poured on them, in a fuller mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for ever hereafter! And
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49814:22"/>that which addes abundant weight to their miſeries,<note place="margin">Nec qui torquet, aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do fatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; nec qui tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetur, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquando moritur, <hi>Bernard, meditat. cap.</hi> 3,</note> is; they ſhall burn, but not diminiſh; they ſhall lye buried in their flames, but not conſume; they ſhall ſeek death, but ſhall not finde it: they ſhall deſire it, but it ſhall flee from them: their puniſhment conſiſts not in the indurance of any proper or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar pain, but in the accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and heap of innumerable torments together. All the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the ſoul, all the ſenſes of the body ſhall have their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall puniſhments, and that which is more, unſeparable, and more then that, eternall: There ſhall be degrees in their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but the leaſt ſhall be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite. For as the wrath and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of <hi>God</hi> toward them is everlaſting, ſo ſhall their preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures be. They enjoy an <hi>eternity</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49814:22"/>like the <hi>Saints,</hi> but not the <hi>Saints eternity;</hi> for their eternity ſhall beginne in horror, and proceed in confuſion: their eternity ſhall purchaſe and yeeld to them, no other fruit but yellings and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, and woe. Their <hi>eternity</hi> is ſuch as turns all things into its own nature: for all things where the damned do inhabit, are eternall. The fire is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: for the breath of God like a river of brimſtone hath kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it, and it ſhall never goe out night nor day; but the ſmoak thereof ſhall aſcend for ever. The worm is eternall, for the conſcience of the damned ſhall be everlaſtingly tormented with the ſenſe of their ſinne: Their worme dyeth not, (ſaith the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi>) and their fire never goeth out. The priſon wherein they are incloſed is eternall. The
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49814:23"/>prayers of the <hi>Church</hi> could open the priſon doors to <hi>Peter,</hi> but no prayers can pierce theſe walls, no power can overthrow them, no time can ruine them; out of Hell is no redemption, no ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, no delivery, <hi>Cruciantur damnati, cruciantur in aeternum.</hi> This is the laſt ſentence of the <hi>Judge,</hi> his irrevocable decree, his immutable and eternall <hi>Judgement</hi> on the damned, which ſhall nevever be reverſed:<note place="margin">Adeſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, abeſſe impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le.</note> there is no appeal will lye from this <hi>Judge;</hi> there is no reverſing this judgement, when the ſentence is once paſt, it ſtands for <hi>eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> Hence it was that the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Church</hi> repeated this ſentence often in their divine ſervice, <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantem me quotidie, &amp; non peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentem, timor mortis conturbat, quia ex inferno nulla eſt redemptio:</hi> Whil'ſt I daily ſinne, but repent
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49814:23"/>not daily as I ought, the fear of death amazeth me, becauſe after this life ended, out of Hell is no redemption. The blood of <hi>Christ</hi> ſhed on <hi>Golgotha,</hi> is fully ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſave all man-kinde, but it belongs not to the damned. If therefore the yoak of repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſeem not ſweet to thee, (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Bernard</hi>) think on that yoak which thou ſhalt be ſure to ſuffer, which is, <hi>Goe ye curſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternal fire.</hi> But the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable thing which is eternall in hell, is, the irrevocable loſſe of the beatificall preſence of <hi>God,</hi> the eternall privation of <hi>Gods</hi> ſight, the uncomfortable want whereof, doth more grieve their hearts, and wound their afflicted ſouls, then all their bodily tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Thus we ſee the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py eſtate and condition of the damned in the other world, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49814:24"/>how the higheſt link in all this chain of ſorrows, wherewith they are environed, is the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perpetuity of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when their reſtleſſe thoughts have carefully runne thorow many thouſands of years, yet will they not then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy one day, one little houre, one minute of reſt and reſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Everlaſting darkneſſe is their portion, they beginne and end a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, with weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. Now ſince this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true, is it poſſible for man ſo to degenerate into a beaſt, as to beleeve theſe things, and not to tremble? Can the knowledge of theſe things ſwim in our brain, without a ſerious and found digeſtion of them into our hearts? when we know, and ſtand convinced, that inexplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, eternall, endleſſe, eaſeleſſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49814:24"/>horrors, without true and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned repentance, abide us here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; and on the other ſide we know not, nor can poſſibly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, with how ſpeedy and ſwift a foot our end approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, nor how ſuddenly we ſhall be ſummoned to give the world our everlaſting farewell. How can ſo ſad and important conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration as this, poſſeſſe our thoughts, &amp; not torment them? Or how can this chuſe but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitter our deareſt pleaſures, and croſſe our indulgence to our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall affections? Did we but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a while with our ſouls, and every one of us in a particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication ſay within himſelf: I am here floating like a ſhip in the ſea of this world, ballaſted on every ſide with the cares, and diſquietings, and miſeries of this life, and I ſaile on with full
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49814:25"/>courſe towards the haven of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity: one little blaſt is able to plunge me irrecoverably into this bottomleſſe gulf, where one houres torment will infinitely exceed, (for the pain of it) an hundred years bitter repentance. And ſhall I now thus ſtanding upon the very battlements of hell, melt in my delights, cheer up my ſelf in the dayes of my youth? ſhall I tire out my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, trifle out my precious time, rob mine eyes of their beloved ſleep, for ſuch things, to the which the time will come, and is haſtening onward, when I muſt bid an everlaſting fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well? Me thinks the thorow meditation of our future ſtate ſhould even ſtrangle our ſenſuall joys in us, and withdraw our hearts from the embracements of this world, eſpecially when
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49814:25"/>we ſhall to our endleſſe ſorrow underſtand, our deareſt contents muſt cloſe, at the laſt, in death and confuſion, and all our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent pleaſures, ſhall yeeld us no other fruit, but their bitter remembrance, to augment our ſorrowes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Wherein the queſtion is anſwered, wherefore a finite ſinne, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed with an infinite pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: wherein alſo is far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhewed, that the ſeverity of Gods justice therein, doth no way diminiſh the greatneſse of his mercy.</head>
                  <p>NOw here ariſeth the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be reſolved; How comes it to paſſe, that our mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and gracious <hi>God,</hi> who is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49814:26"/>ſo infinite in his goodneſſe, and ſo abundant in his love, whoſe praiſes the Prophet <hi>David</hi> am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifies in his 136. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> twenty ſeven times together, with this concluſion, <hi>for his mercy endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for ever:</hi> how can it ſtand, that this our God, whoſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is exalted above all his works, ſhould be thus infinitely merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and yet ſo infinitely juſt too, as to inflict upon a finite ſin, an infinite puniſhment, that he ſhould continue millions of years, yea, to <hi>everlaſtingnes,</hi> in the avengement of thoſe ſinnes, which were committed as it were in a moment of time, ſo that he who hath offended but temporally, ſhould be bound to ſuffer paines eternally? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, we ſhall ſufficiently vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and clear <hi>Gods</hi> righteous dealing towards us herein, if we
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49814:26"/>meaſure his juſtice but by our own rules:<note place="margin">Scelus non temporis longitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine metien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt. <hi>Aug. de Civitat. Dei lib.</hi> 21. <hi>cap</hi> 11.</note> * for doth any law proportion out the time of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to that meaſure of time only, in which the offence is committed? Shall the priſoner lye no longer in the Goale, then he was committing his villany? Do not we here amongſt us of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſee ſome offences which were ſuddenly thought of, and as ſoon executed, yet puniſhed with endleſſe, dateleſſe baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which in compariſon to this life, bear a proportion with eternity? Now if the wiſdom of man doth follow this rule in proportioning of puniſhments, weighing offences by the foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the fact; Shall we deny <hi>God</hi> the righteous <hi>Judge</hi> of all the world, the ſame liberty over the works of his own hands? Again, if this will not ſatisfy our
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49814:27"/>inquiſitive mindes, let us but take our own hearts to task, and ſift them to the bottom, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially weigh what a world of pollution, and deceit, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſſe, is lodged in them: and then certainly, we ſhall finde matter enough againſt our ſelves without farther inquiry, for our endleſſe condemnation: our own conſciences will teſtify to the confuſion of our faces, that juſt is the <hi>Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nec in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſta ejus gratia, nec crudelis poteſt eſſe juſtitia. <hi>Aug. de Civit, De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> lib.</hi> 21. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> and juſt are his <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> that all the waies of the <hi>Lord</hi> are mercy and truth, that his grace is not unjuſt, nor his Juſtice cruell. Adde hereunto, that the fault, of its own nature, is infinite, becauſe it is a ſin againſt an infinite majeſty. <hi>Gods</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice being infinite, the viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therereof by ſinne, muſt needs contract an infinite debt; becauſe in ſinning we
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49814:27"/>rob God of his glory, which we muſt needs repay him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: Now the ſatisfaction of an infinite debt, muſt needs be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, either in reſpect of time, or meaſure. And becauſe a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite veſſell is not able to hold or comprehend an infinite wrath, foraſmuch as we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear <hi>Gods</hi> indignation, <hi>prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter immenſitatem doloris,</hi> we muſt of neceſſity ſatisfie his Juſtice, <hi>duratione temporis;</hi> the long continuance of our ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, muſt ſupply what is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the weight of our puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Again, he that dies in his ſin without repentance, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends as much as if he had ſinned eternally: <hi>quia omnis peccator eſt in aeternum, ſi in eternum vixiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, in aeternum peccaſſet; i.e.</hi> had he lived eternally, his ſinne had extended to the length
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49814:28"/>of his daies,<note place="margin">Peccandi volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem non amiſit, ſed vitam. <hi>Greg.</hi>
                     </note> * for a man ſooner ceaſeth to live, then to love his ſinne, and therefore God may juſtly after many thouſand years torments in Hell, iterate their torments to the damned: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if they had longer abode in their ſinfull fleſh, they would ſtill have perpetuated their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tranſgreſſions. Oh let not then ſinfull fleſh contend with its maker, let not us prye into the Heavens, not curiouſly ſearch into the ſecrets of <hi>Gods</hi> will, to finde a reaſon of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of a ſinner to perpetuall puniſhment, but rather in the lowlines of our hearts, crye out with <hi>Daniel,</hi> O <hi>Lord,</hi> righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe belongs unto thee, but to us open ſhame, becauſe we have rebelled againſt thee: let us caſt down our ſouls at the foot of his grace, and humbly acknowledge
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49814:28"/>in the ſenſe of our deformities, that juſt is the <hi>Lord,</hi> and juſt are his judgements. Our weak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings can no way fathom the depth of his counſells; his wiſdom is unſearchable, and all his wayes are truth: but did we truly apprehend the nature of our ſinnes, we would never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine at the weight of <hi>Gods</hi> Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For whereas <hi>God</hi> made man a noble creature, both beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and glorious, and after ſtamped on him his own Image, righteouſneſſe and true holines, how ſtrangely hath his ſinne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robed him of all his excellencies? what rebellion hath it ſetled in all his members? what ſtaines and pollutions hath it wrought in all his faculties? It is our ſin which hath unjoynted the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacies, and ſocieties of the dumb creatures, and hath armed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49814:29"/>them with an antipathy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion one againſt another. It is ſinne which hath ſo ſtrangely altered the manners and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our times, that hath turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mens brows into braſſe, and their hearts into ſtones, and their hands into violence, and their tongues into Scorpions. It is ſin which hath uſhered in theſe ſad diviſions into our Church and ſtate, and drawn out ſuch ſtreams of blood in every corner of the land, and made the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the kingdome trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. It is ſinne that is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and ſource of all thoſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, ſchiſmes, hereſies, ſtrange opinions that are lately ſprung up amongſt us. And ſurely we may write it one of the ſaddeſt of our miſeries, and that which wil fall heavily ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in the end (if ſome great
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49814:29"/>humiliation prevent not the judgement) that theſe things are ſuffered without controle. And here give me leave a little to vent my troubled thoughts, Though I wander from the point in hand, yet for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake I cannot hold my peace. Have we not ſworne, have we not deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, publikely in the open Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, in the ſight of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men; and with as grave and ſad ſolemnity, as wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome could deviſe, <hi>lifted up our hands to the moſt high God, ſaying that we would ſincerely, really, and conſtantly, by the grace of God in our ſeverall places and callings, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the extirpation of Hereſy, Sciſme, and whatſoever ſhould be found contrary to ſound Doctrine, and the power of Godlines.</hi> Yet notwithſtanding this deep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement on our ſouls. How
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49814:30"/>many fearfull errors, what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of fancies do uncontrolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly abound in every corner of the land? Doth not every man act what ſeems good in his own eyes? Is not every wanton we impunitively ſuffered to make an idoll of his own way,? and to draw Diſciples after him? Me thinks its worthy our moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thoughts, how ſadly, how compaſſionately the reformed Churches do reſent our home diſtractions. See what the <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachrian</hi> Churches have writ <hi>to our Reverend Aſſembly of Divines, upon this occaſion.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Judicent conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientiae veſtrae, quomodo omnium Hereſium genus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultum permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicia ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſem i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na impunè ſpargi, &amp; prophana errorum dogmata, paſſim in vulgus proferri poſſint in illa civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, quae tam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſo, ſancto, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vero jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe coram Deo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinxit, ad omnes er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rores, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſesſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata de domo Dei ejicienda.</note> * <hi>Let your own conſciences judge</hi> (ſay they) <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Hereſies of all kindes can paſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed? manifold ſeeds of Schiſme be ſpread without controll, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Doctrines of errors be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vented in publike in that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which by ſo expreſſe, ſo ſacred
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49814:30"/>ſo ſevere an Oath, hath bound it ſelf in the preſence of God, to caſt out all Hereſies, Errors, Schiſmes, out of the houſe of God.</hi> Hence ye may obſerve how loud a peal our Church diviſions ring tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row out the world; Our friends pity us, our foes deride us, and neuters ſtand amazed at our doings: and certainly God is not pleaſed with our wayes. For God is the God of order, and not of confuſion; the God of peace, not of diviſion.</p>
                  <p>In vain it is to expect any hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, or peacefull dayes, or that we ſhall ſee a well grounded ſettlement in Church and ſtate, ſo long as turbulent ſpirits have ſo much line and latitude to their fancies. And ſurely it is now high time, it is high time for us all in our ſeverall places, ſince we ſtand every day hover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49814:31"/>between time and eternity, to minde our ſacred vowes, and to lay our ſolemn Covenants cloſely to our hearts, and ask our conſciences, how faithfully we have performed them; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the particular wherein we now inſiſt.</p>
                  <p>Errors in opinion are of as dangerous conſequence, as er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rors in practice; and therefore happy would it be for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, if they that move in the higheſt Sphears would all come in as with one ſhoulder, and make it the chiefeſt buſineſſe of their ſouls, that the Lord may be one, and his name one through the Kingdome. Now if you tell me I here digreſſe from the point in hand, I readily grant it: for theſe diſtracted times have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed me, and obſtructed me in my way. But now I return
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49814:31"/>You ſee the diſmall fruits of ſinne, what deſtruction it hath wrought in all the earth? what havock in our State? what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion in the Church? what rentings of affections in the hearts of men?</p>
                  <p>Oh that we did ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of, and ſoundly digeſt the meditation of theſe things? For had we but hearts to underſtand, and eyes to ſee the deformity of our ſinnes, and did unpartially compare the ſtain and pollution of them, with the pureneſſe of <hi>Gods</hi> nature, and the brightnes of his Majeſty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> how ſhould we be confounded in our ſouls, with the ſight of our own filthineſſe? How ready ſhould we be rather to admire <hi>Gods</hi> patience, then queſtion his ſeverity? How ſhould we tremble at his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Majeſty, and dread his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49814:32"/>and juſtly fear what we have worthily deſerved, his everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting judgement: but if now on the other ſide we adviſedly look into <hi>Gods</hi> gracious proceedings towards us, and his loving indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in reſtraining his incenſed diſpleaſure, notwithſtanding our infinite provocations, and in ſhewing us a way to eſcape his fury; I know not whether we ſhall finde greater cauſe to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate his juſtice, or admire his mercy. For true it is, as ſaith Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deus adeo bonus eſt, ut malum nunquam ſincret, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi adeo potens ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iflet, ut ex malo bonum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liceret. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                     </note> So <hi>good</hi> is our <hi>God,</hi> that he would never have ſuffer'd us to fal, had not his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er been ſuch, that he could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract matter out of our ſinfulnes, to advance his own glory. Oh how unſearchable, how bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe, how ſurpaſſing the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of men and Angels is the love of <hi>God</hi> towards us!
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49814:32"/>whither can we goe? which way can we caſt our eyes, where we ſhall not behold the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble foot-ſteps of his mercy? If we look upward, his mercy reacheth unto the Heavens, ſaith <hi>David:</hi> If downward, they that goe down into the deep, ſee the wonders of <hi>God,</hi> ſaith the ſame <hi>Prophet,</hi> and his mercies in the great waters. If round about us, thoſe that put their truſt in the <hi>Lord,</hi> mercy embraceth them on every ſide. And hence it is that the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> ſo diverſly ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the love of <hi>God</hi> in ſeverall places of that Epiſtle, by ſundry appellations or epithetes, as his <hi>love, his great love, his abundant love,</hi> his love paſſing knowledge: again, the riches of his glory, <hi>the riches of his grace, the riches of his mercy; God</hi> who is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49814:33"/>ſaith the Apoſtle, who is <hi>rich in mercy</hi> through his love, his <hi>great love,</hi> even when we were dead by ſinnes, hath quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned us together in <hi>Christ, Epheſ.</hi> 2.4. The Apoſtle alſo in the ſame Epiſtle, and firſt chapter, expreſſeth the Lord, great in his power, abundant in his wiſdom, but rich, exceeding rich in his mercy, And why rich in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy only? Is not the Lord rich in <hi>Angels,</hi> rich in the <hi>Saints,</hi> rich in the <hi>Heavens?</hi> Hath he not created the Clouds, founded the Seas, wiſely compoſed the whole frame of nature? And is he yet rich only in mercy? True it is; the earth is the Lords, and the fulneſſe thereof: all that we have, all that we are, is his, but his mercy hath an excellency in it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all his creatures; yea (If I may ſo ſpeak) obove all his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49814:33"/>above his Juſtice; Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy (ſaith the Apoſtle) rejoyceth againſt condemnation: Above his power; <hi>Jacob</hi> wreſtled with God and overcame him; above his greatnes: for ſuch was the unexpreſſible condiſcention of the Almighty, that although he were high and excellent, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited eternity, yet did he humble himſelf, to behold things done in Heaven &amp; earth; for there is nothing doth more illuſtrate <hi>Gods</hi> omnipotency, then his mercy. It was no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail that <hi>God</hi> ſhould make the Heavens, becauſe he is power it ſelf; or that he ſhould frame the earth; becauſe he is ſtrength it ſelf; or that he ſhould govern the times; becauſe he is wiſdom it ſelf; or that he ſhould give breath to all creatures, becauſe he is life it ſelf; But herein chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49814:34"/>is <hi>God</hi> to be magnified, that he who is infinitely juſt, ſhould yet be mercifull to ſinners; yea, to ſinners while they wallow in their blood, while they reſt in ſinnes, while they have no eye to look after him, no heart to embrace him, no foot to follow him, no tongue to glorifie him, but lye wofully plunged in the dregs of their pollutions? Oh the unſpeakable goodnes of our <hi>God,</hi> who hath ſo graciouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited thoſe ſheep, who are ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily ſtrayed from him; nay, who doth with a<note n="*" place="margin">Omnipo, tentiſſima facilitate homines ad ſeip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertit De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus facit. <hi>Aug. ad vita.</hi>
                     </note> loving vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, irreſiſtably call thoſe who have trampled on his graces, and rejected his love. But what ſhould move the Creator of all things, who hath been thus infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely provoked, who is armed both with power to ſtrike, and means to be avenged, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49814:34"/>his enemies? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, there is, there can be no other reaſon alleadged, but that which <hi>David</hi> ſo often iterates, <hi>becauſe he is gracious, and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy endureth for ever.</hi> But me thinks I hear the afflicted ſoul bewail it ſelf: here is a fountain of mercy indeed, had I heart to draw out of it: Can his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe extend to me, who am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but worms and duſt, and wounds and ſores, and corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions? Who can give him no oblation but my ſinnes, no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice but my ſorrow. What confidence now can I have in this love? What ſtrength in this mercy? Who ever thou art, that art thus, and no better diſpoſed to receive the grace of thy God, bring forth this ſmall proviſion, offer this ſacrifice upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. Since thou haſt nothing
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49814:35"/>elſe to part with, ſurrender up thy ſinnes, yeeld him thy luſts, renounce thy whole intereſt in thy ſinfull delights, in thy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate affections<note n="*" place="margin">Nullius rei tantum in inferno eſt, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priae vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis. <hi>Alſted.</hi>
                     </note> and then thy ſorrowfull ſpirit ſhall be a ſacrifice to <hi>God,</hi> thy wounded and broken heart he will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe; <hi>I am with him,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>who is of an humbled ſpirit, &amp; that trembleth at my words.</hi> We have his own word for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, we have his promiſe for it, we have his oath for it. He is faithfull ſaith the Apoſtle, who hath promiſed; he is faithfull, he cannot deny himſelf.<note n="*" place="margin">Supe rate ſeipſum poteſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertos mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerando, negare ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum non poteſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcricordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am deſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo.</note> He may overcome himſelf by pittying the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken ones, but he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelf, by forſaking his pitty. For how can he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelf to us, who hath given himſelf, for us? How
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49814:35"/>can he deny us his mercy, who hath given us his life?</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>The end of the firſt book.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:49814:36"/>
               <head>THE SECOND BOOK OF <hi>ETERNITY.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Containing an exhortation to holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, grounded upon the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Eternity.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He very ſoule and life of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, conſiſts in the life of a Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as for outward for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities, they plauſibly ſerve to ſhew forth a good man to the eye of the world, but cannot make him ſuch; it's true, exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall actions adorn our profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49814:36"/>but it is, where grace and goodneſſe ſeaſons them, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe where the ſap, and juyce and vigour of religion is not ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the ſoul, a man is but like a goodly heart-ſhaken <hi>Oak,</hi> whoſe beauty will turne into rotteneſſe, and his end will be the fire. It was the ſaying of <hi>Machiavell;</hi> that the appearance of vertue was more to be deſired then vertue in ſelf. But <hi>Socrates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>meer</hi> naturaliſt, adviſed better, who ſaid, the good man is only wiſe. Certainly our glorious ſhews, and high applauſes, and exaltations amongſt the ſonnes of men, will prove but miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble comforters in the cloſe of our age, when the days of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe come. O then as we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the eternall welfare of our poor ſouls, let us be what we would ſeem. Letus tume our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49814:37"/>words into actions,<note place="margin">Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alis videri, vis talis eſſe debes. <hi>Gerh Med.</hi>
                     </note> our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge into affection, and our ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation into practiſe. Let us not onely in a generall and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed manner acknowledge <hi>God,</hi> but rather labour to know him;<note n="*" place="margin">Let us not think it enough to beleeve that <hi>Chriſt</hi> came as a <hi>Saviour</hi> into the world, but endeavour rather by a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar, perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faith to make him our own.</note> Alas what avails it my ſoul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that <hi>Christ</hi> ſhed forth his blood for the ſinnes of many; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he died not for me? What joy to my heart, that Chriſt is riſen for the juſtification of ſinners, if he be not my portion? what comfort to my diſtreſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that Chriſt is come a light into the world, if I ſit in darkneſſe and in the ſhadow of death? What confidence of protection can I have from hence,<note place="margin">Non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectio, niſi in te quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat <hi>Gerh. Med.</hi> Sitſcopus vitae Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, quem ſ quaris in via, ut aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequaris in parria.</note> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a carefull ſhepherds over his flock, if I am none of that ſheep fold? Other let it be the chief deſire of our ſouls, and the utmoſt extent of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49814:37"/>our endeavours, not onely to confeſſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but to bring him home to our hearts, to feel him, to affect him, to live in him, to depend on him, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to him: let us willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare, and cheerfully follow the voice of that ſweet guide, who is both the way, and the journies end; that loving Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian who comes to our wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed conſciences with healing in his wings; that meek and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Lamb, who powred forth for us tears of anguiſh, and tears of love; tears of anguiſh to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem our ſouls, and tears of love to compaſſionate our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Now what a preſſing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion have we here to live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, who thus died for us; to make him our joy who hath borne our ſorrows; to fix him in our hearts, who for our ſakes
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49814:38"/>was fixed to the Croſſe?<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>otus tibi figa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, qui totu spro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te figeb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</note> How ſhould we mourn in our ſouls, and weep in ſecret for him? <hi>quem totus mundus, tota element<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> lugebant,</hi> at whoſe ſufferings the graves opened, the Sunne ſhut in his light, the earth trembled, and the whole frame of Heaven in his nature and kinde expreſſed its ſorrow. One of the <hi>Rabins,</hi> when he read what bitter tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the <hi>Meſſias</hi> ſhould ſuffer, when he came into the world, (cryed out) <hi>veniat Meſſias, at eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> non videam,</hi> Let the <hi>Meſſias</hi> come, but let me not ſee him. Did his torments ſeem ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall to the ſpectator, what were they then in the ſufferer? If ſo ghaſtly to the ſight, what were they in the ſuſtaining? But what ſhould we doe now? Shall we raile on <hi>Judas</hi> that betrayed him, or on <hi>Peter</hi> that denyed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49814:38"/>him, or the <hi>Jews</hi> that pierced him, or the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> that forſook him? No, no, let us look into our own hearts, examine our own ways. Do we not make his wounds bleed afreſh with our ſinnes? doe we not nayl him to the Croſſe again with our pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? doe we not grinde him in our oppreſſions, and as it were maſſacre him in our murders? What ſinne have we ever forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for his ſake? what inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate affection have we abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his love? Can we ſay, and ſay truly, that we ever ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a diſh from our bellies, or one houre from our ſleep, or one faſhion from our backs, for his ſake? and doe we thus requite our Redeemer? Was Chriſt all in gore blood for our ſinnes, and ſhall we ſwim in pleaſure? Did Chriſt indure ſuch contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49814:39"/>of ſinners, and cannot we put up a ſlight diſgrace.<note n="*" place="margin">Deus tuus par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus factus eſt, &amp; tu te magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficas, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ina nivit ſe mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſts, &amp; tu vermicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus intu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſcis.</note> Was <hi>Christ</hi> ſtretched on the Croſſe, and ſhall we ſtretch our ſelves on beds of down? Did Chriſt ſuch down vineger for us, and ſhall we ſurfet with plenty? Was Chriſt crowned with thorns, and ſhall we crown our ſelves with Roſe buds? O let it ſhame us, to bear ſo dainty a body un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo dolefull a head. And think we with our ſelves, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinne againſt God muſt needs be more, then men commonly eſteem it, for which no way of expiation could be made, but by the bitter paſſion of Chriſt. Oh then let us not think any thing to dear for him, who thought nothing to dear for us. We have an ineſtimable price, a glorious inheritance ſet before us, let us carefully embrace all
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49814:39"/>thoſe means that may further our progreſſe: as the hearing of the Word, receaving of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, earneſt and conſtant prayer to <hi>Almighty God:</hi> Let us ſtrive as we ought, preſſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with all violence. The woman in the Goſpell which was ſo long viſited with her bloudy iſſue, it was her holy<note n="*" place="margin">Victa eſt ad vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiam, quia vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenta ad victoriam.</note> violence and preſſing our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, that procured health for her body, and pardon for her ſoul; Let this be our endeavour, let us never think our ſelves farre enough in the way to Heaven, but prepare our hearts ſtill, and lay hold on every advantage, that may further us in our jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Behold now is the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table time, now is the day of Salvation, whilſt you have time then doe good unto all: whilſt you have the light, walk as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49814:40"/>of the light: Judge thy ſelf here, that thou be not judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Lord hereafter. Let not thy eyes ſlumber, nor thy temples take any reſt, till tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> haſt found our an habitation in thine heart, for the mighty <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Jacob.</hi> Remember him, as <hi>David</hi> did, in thy bed, and think upon him when thou art wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: God ſaid of the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> I gave her time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of her fornication, and ſhe repented not. O let us not give our good God the like occaſion, to ſecond the ſame complaint againſt us. Behold, God now graciouſly calls us, and offers us his mercy: He ſtands at the door and knocks: Hear his ſweet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation; <hi>Open unto me, my ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, my love, my dove, my unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed: for my head is full of dew, and my locks with the drops of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49814:40"/>night,</hi> Song of <hi>Solomon.</hi> chap. 5. What a ſtrange humiliation is here, for the king of kings to wait to have mercy! Let us ariſe and open ſpeedily to our beloved: to day while it is called to day, let us heare his voice, let us not put off our time, as <hi>Felix</hi> did S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Paul, goe for this preſent time, and when I have a convenient lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I will heare thee,</hi> as if the time preſent were not the fitteſt. Let us not ſtifle the checks of our conſciences, or ſay, as <hi>Festus</hi> to <hi>Agrippa, to morrow thou ſhalt heare him.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Non quaerit Deus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationem in voce corvina, ſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſionem in gemitu columbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</note> All procraſtinations in this caſe are dangerous. Let us therefore take hold of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whilſt occaſion ſerves us. If we ſhut out our welbeloved, he will be gon. Therefore let our hearts even melt within us, whilſt he ſpeaks to us in his word. If we anſwer not when
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49814:41"/>he calls us, then ſhall we call, and he will not anſwer. The <hi>Stork</hi> and the <hi>Crane,</hi> and the <hi>Swallow</hi> in the aire know their ſeaſons, and obſerve their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed times, how much more ſhould man, eſpecially ſince times and moments, how long we ſhall enjoy them, are not in our own power, but in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God. The Angel in the Revelation ſwore by him, that liveth for ever, that time ſhould be no more. The time paſt can never be recalled, let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take the preſent time: For the time paſt was and is not, the time preſent is, but ſhall not be, and of the future, we can promiſe to our ſelves no fruition. But alas ſuch is our blindneſſe, ſuch an obduration is grown over our hearts, that we underſtand theſe things, but feel them not; we
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49814:41"/>have them ſwimming in our mindes, but embrace them not in our affections. The beſt of us may take up that complaint of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Teneo in memoria, ſcribo in charta, ſed non habeo in vita. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                     </note> * who aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of himſelf, that his deſires were better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his practice. Our vows are in Heaven, but our hearts on earth; our deſires are towards our home, but our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours flagge in the way, and we faint in our journey: we have Heavenly hopes, but earthly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; we all covet after hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, but we would take no pains for it; we would enjoy Chriſt in his benefits, but we refuſe to partake with him in his ſufferings; <hi>volumus aſſequi Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum, ſed non ſequi,</hi> we would ſhare willingly with our <hi>Saviour</hi> in his Crown, but not in his combat; nay, oftentimes we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <hi>God</hi> for ſuch graces as we
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49814:42"/>are loath to obtain: like Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who prayed for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency with a proviſo, Lord, give me continency, but not yet; nay ſuch is our intolerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and pollution of heart, that at the ſame inſtant, when our hands are lift up to God for the pardon of old ſinnes, our heads are working in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving of new; as <hi>Salvian</hi> hath it, <hi>dum verbis praeterita mala plangimus, ſenſu futura medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur.</hi> Thus we draw nigh to God with our lips, when our hearts are farre from him, our affections are buried in the things of this life. Excellent is that ſaying of <hi>Iſidorus,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Regnum hoc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piternum, ex omni parte bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, omnibus promiſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; tamen de illo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum inter nos ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que enim eſt qui de hoc com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorat, hoc uxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, hoc li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beris, toti hoc fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat? <hi>Iſid.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oelum negligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram non retine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Dei favorem non ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirimus, mundi perdimus.</note> The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, ſaith he, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, bleſſed every way, and promiſed to all men, but who is there almoſt that ſpends one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the ſerious meditation of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49814:42"/>it? What man is there that ever talks to his wife, to his children, to his family of ſuch a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? We can riot in the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of our native ſoile, but we bluſh to ſpeak of, and are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to commend our true coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, our everlaſting home. In our dealings about the things of this life, our underſtandings are ready enough to apprehend them, and our hearts to entertain them, and our tongues to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of them; but in things that belong to the eternall ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſouls, how deep is our ſilence, how flow our ſpeech, how unskilfull our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions?</p>
                  <p>Thus we forſake Heaven for theſe things, which at laſt will forſake us, and trifle out our time in things that will not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit us. Hovv farre are men novv
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49814:43"/>adaies from that ſweet reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saint <hi>Hierome? Let others, ſaith he, live in their ſtatues, in their coſtly monuments: I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Pauls Coat with his Heavenly graces, then the purple of Kings with their Kingdomes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O that we would look thus lowly upon our ſelves; we are Chriſtians in profeſſion, O let us be ſuch in practice: ſeeing that God hath made us ſtewards of his treaſures, let us improve them to the benefit of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. Hath God given us abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his bleſſings? Let us not hide our talents in a napkin: let us ſend our good works be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us into Heaven: theſe ſlender gifts, which thou doeſt cheerfully diſtribute in this world, will procure thee an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall compenſation in the world to come. That ſweet
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49814:43"/>ſpeech of Saint <hi>John</hi> is worth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, <hi>bleſſed are thoſe that dye in the Lord, they rest from their labours, and their works follow them.</hi> When our deareſt friends, our ſweeteſt pleaſures, our moſt glorious titles of honour, the world it ſelf, yea even our life it ſelf ſhall glide away like a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and turn to duſt, then ſhall our good works follow us, <hi>non tranſeunt opera noſtra</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>ſicut tranſire videntur, ſed velut aeternitatis ſemina jaciuntur;</hi> our good deeds die not with us, but they are ſowne in earth, and ſpring in Heaven; they are an inexhauſtible fountain, that ſhall never be dried up: a durable ſpring, that ſhall never fail. They are acts of time, ſhort in their performance, yet eternall in their recompence; they build up for us, through the mercies of our
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49814:44"/>
                     <hi>God,</hi> an everlaſting foundation for the time to come.</p>
                  <p>Loe then here we have ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us <hi>viam ad regnum,</hi> the way to our eternity; let us goe on herein without intermiſſion; preſſe forward with violence, &amp; ſtrive to attain the crown.<note n="*" place="margin">Opulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia nimis multa eſt aeternitas, ſed niſi perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranter quaeſita nunquam inver itur <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rnard</hi>
                     </note> Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall joy is an abundant treaſure, an everlaſting wealth, but it is not given, ſave to them that ſeek it; yea that ſeek it with their whole hearts. Certainly did we as truly know, as we ſhall one day undoubtedly feel the bitter fruit, that our luke-warm profeſſion, our groſſe ſtupidity, and utter neglect of our everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſtate, will produce and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us in the end, all our thoughts and language, all our affections and inclinations would be more eagerly imployed, and more faithfully exerciſed in our
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49814:44"/>preparations for that building given of God, a houſe not made with hands, but eternall in the Heavens. Oh how ſenſeleſſe are we, how ſtupid in our ſelves,<note place="margin">Illud pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter quod peccamus, amitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; pecca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um ipſum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinemus.</note> and wickedly injurious to our own welfare, who for a ſmall gain, a ſading pleaſure, a fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive honour wound our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and hazard our ſouls, to ſtand as it were on the brink of hell?</p>
                  <p>The whole world, promiſed for a reward, cannot perſwade us to endure one momentary tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in fire: And yet in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed courſe of our lives we dread not, we quake not at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting burnings. But ô thou delicious and dainty ſoul, who cheriſheſt thy ſelf in the joy of thy heart, and the delight of thine eyes, whoſe belly is thy God, and the world thy Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe!
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49814:45"/>O, bethink thy ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, before that gloomy day, that day of clouds and thick darkneſſe, that day of deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and confuſion approach, when all the inhabitants of the earth ſhall mourn and lament, and all faces (as the Prophet <hi>Joel</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>ſhall gather blackneſse,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the time of their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is come. Alas, with what a dolefull heart, and weeping eye, and drooping countenance, and trembling loyns, wilt thou at the laſt and great Aſſize look upon <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> when he ſhall moſt gloriouſly appear with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Angels in flaming fire, to render vengeance on them that know him not? What a cold damp will ſeize upon thy ſoul, when thou ſhalt behold him, whom thou haſt all thy life long neglected in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49814:45"/>deſpiſed in his members, rejected in his love; when thou ſhalt ſee the judgement ſeat, the † books opened,<note place="margin">Fiet aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio libro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merita univ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſibi ipſis &amp; caeteris, innoteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</note> thy ſinnes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, yea all the ſecret coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells of thy heart, after a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull manner, manifeſted and laid open to the eye of the whole world? What horrour and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity of ſpirit will poſſeſſe thee, to view and behold, but the ry ſolemnities and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which accompany this Judgement; vvhen thou ſhalt ſee the Heavens burn, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments melt, the earth tremble, the ſea roar, the ſun turne into darkneſſe, and the moon into blood? And novv vvhat ſhall be thy refuge, vvhere ſhall be thy ſuccour? ſhalt thou raign, becauſe thou cloatheſt thy ſelf in Cedar? ſhalt thou be ſafe, becauſe vvith the Eagle thou
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49814:46"/>haſt ſet thy neaſt on high? O no, it is not now the greatneſſe of thy ſtate, nor the abundance of thy wealth, nor the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy place, nor the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of thy worth, or wit, or learning, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> avail thee ought, either to avoid thy doom, or prorogue thy judgement. All ſtates and conditions of men are alike, when they appear at this barre. There the Prince muſt lay down his crown, and the Pear his robes, and the Judge his purple, and the Captain his banner; All muſt promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly attend to give in their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, and to receive according to that they have done, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be good, or whether it be evil. Here on earth great men, and glorious in the eye of the world, ſo long as they can hold their habitations in the earth,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49814:46"/>have both countenance to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and power to protect them from the injuries of the times: but when the diſmall face of that terrible day ſhall ſhew it ſelf, then ſhall they finde no eye to pity, nor arm to help, nor palace to defend, nor rocks to ſhelter, nor mountains to cover them from the preſence of him that ſits upon the throne, and from the wrath of the lamb. Give me the moſt inſolent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the moſt undaunted ſoul, that now breaths under the cope of Heaven, who now fears not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny created nature, no not <hi>God</hi> himſelf, yet when he ſhall heare that terrible ſound, Ariſe ye dead and come to judgement, how will his heart even melt, and his bowels quiver within him; when he ſhall have his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere judge above him, and hell
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49814:47"/>beneath him, and his worm within him, and fire round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him. O then whoſoever thou art, die unto thy ſins, and unto thy pleaſures here; that thou mayeſt live to <hi>God</hi> hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; *<note place="margin">Sic tibi cave, ut ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veas teip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</note> goe out of thy ſelf, judge and condemn thine own ſoul, for thy ſinnes againſt <hi>God</hi> in this world, that ſo thou mayeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably receive thy ſentence of abſolution in the world to come. Let us learn to be wiſe in time; let our ſorrow for ſinne antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate and prevent our puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>ſatius eſt &amp; ſuavius fonte purgari quàm igne:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In inferno exomlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſis non eſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nec pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentia tunc tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibui po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpto tempore paeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di.</note> He that grieves not heartily for his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions here, ſhall woefully ſmart for them hereafter. In hell there is no redemption for the time paſt, no confeſſion, no repentance, but a ſad and heavy exchange, and moſt uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49814:47"/>tranſlation, from a ſhort and paſſing joy, to an endleſſe, eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>Surely all the preſſures and vexing diſtempers, that befall us in this life; all the croſſes, which the envy, either of men or evil Angels can throw upon us, are nothing, if compared to eternall miſeries. <hi>Sapienti ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil magnum videri poteſt, cui aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis nota eſt magnitudo.</hi> What if with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> I underwent labours and perills, hunger and thirſt, iniuries and reproaches, what is all this to eternitie?</p>
                  <p>What if I did bear in my fleſh the moſt exquiſite pains and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter torments, that created nature is capable of, yet what were all this to eternitie? For all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities and alterations, which happen to us under the ſun, have their periods, which they cannot
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49814:48"/>paſſe: however they diſquiet us for the time, yet as the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, <hi>the end ſhall be at the appointed time,</hi> God will perform that which he hath appointed for me, ſaith <hi>Iob:</hi> yet <hi>uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad tempus haec omnia,</hi> the end ſhall be at the appointed time. But of this eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie there will be no end, no bounds can limit it, no time ſhall determine it. Certainly, firſt or laſt there will happen to thee ſuch an evening, as ſhall have no morning to follow; or elſe ſuch a morning, as ſhall never ſee the cloſe of the ſun: And therefore let not the vaniſhing cares, &amp; tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie diſquietings of this world over deeply poſſeſſe thy heart; but rather let the whole ſtream of thy meditations run upon thy latter end; that at the time of thy diſſolution; (thy affection being wholy alienated from the world)
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49814:48"/>thy thoughts may aſcend before, whither thy ſoule is coming af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: So ſhall thy ſufferings here, make way for thy crown here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
                  <p>But how few, ô how few, I ſay, are there that weigh theſe things? How few do make it their daily task to meditate on the evils to come? They credit not ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports; for they care not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve what they are unwilling to practiſe: Hence it is that they go on ſo ſecurely in their courſe, as if there were no heaven, no hell, no <hi>God,</hi> no eternity. Thus we na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally deſire our dayes ſhould be as happy as they are long, and being miſerably inſenſible of the ſorrows to come, we raſhly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſelves to an irrevocable downfall.<note n="*" place="margin">Nos ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, qui mortis noſtrae ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equimur. <hi>Greg.</hi>
                     </note> Without ſenſe or ſorrow wee run merrily to hell, where we ſhall everlaſtingly
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49814:49"/>feel what we did never fear, <hi>death and darkneſse,</hi> weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and gnaſhing of teeth. O how different are our times from thoſe of our Anceſtors? They were not more rigidly ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, then we are vainly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure.</p>
                  <p>How did they pine their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and afflict their ſouls, cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their moſt precious luſts, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their friends, their lands, their inheritance, yea their Crowns and Kingdoms; nay which is more, through the rigid and auſtere obſervation of their ſtrict and ſevere laws, expoſe themſelves to the hazard and danger of their deareſt lives, and thruſt themſelves as it were out of the world, and forgo all ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie with men? And wherefore all this, but that they might disburden themſelves the better
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49814:49"/>by theſe means from all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly allurements; ſettle and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their hearts in a good pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration towards their home; and to enliven their affections, and inflame their mindes to a more ſerious contemplation of the joyes to come? Me thinks the conſideration of theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, ſhould ſtrongly invite us to a more ſerious meditation of our future ſtate, eſpecially if we remember how ſwiftly our dayes draw to an end, and how ſoon we are involved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting darkneſſe. For alas, what is our life here, <hi>Tota haec vita unius horulae mors eſt,</hi> one hour at the laſt will ſwallow up all our live-long daies. Let us the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not fear being ſo near our home, let no ſtorms affright us, being ſo near our haven: let us examine our accounts, and caſt up our rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konings,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49814:50"/>that we may be able to give up a good account at the laſt day. Certain it is, what ever we goe about; whatſoever, be the ſcope of our endeavours; we eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day come nearer to the end of our courſe, every houre is a nevv ſtep onvvard.</p>
                  <p>So ſoon as ever a man enters this mortall life, he beginnes a conſtant journey unto death, <hi>quicquid temporis vivitur, de ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio vivendi tollitur: i. e.</hi> Each part of time that we paſſe, cuts off ſo much from our life, and the remainder ſtill decreaſeth; So that our whole life is nothing but a courſe or paſſage unto death, wherein one can neither ſtay nor ſlack his pace. This we know, our daily experience doth confirm this truth: and yet do we perſiſt as ſecurely, as ever in our trade of ſinne: <hi>Aegrè abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>himur
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49814:50"/>ab ijs quibus aſsueſcimus, i. e.</hi> we are hardly drawn from thoſe things which cuſtom and time hath inured us unto. It is a grievous burthen to a licentious heart to be drawn off from dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fare, full cups, and good company. We lye as dead men, and ſenſeles in our damned pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, even drowned in our voluptu ouſnes, like brute beaſts, filled up, and pampered for the day of ſlaughter. Thus with the full ſtream of our endeavours we plod on in the habituall courſe of provoking the patience of a long ſuffering God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſenſe of our ſinne, untill our ſhort dayes begin to ſhut in, and our evening approach; at which time the weakneſſe of our bodies, and the ſtrength of our ſinnes, make us as unable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, as we were before unwill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49814:51"/>We many times, through the incitement of ſome good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, beginne well, but fail in the execution;<note n="*" place="margin">Fatemur crimina, ſed ſic fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temur, ut in ipſa confeſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne non dolemus. <hi>Calv.</hi>
                     </note> we make faire promiſes, but we doe not ſecond them in our practice; but let us not deceive our ſelves, <hi>God</hi> will not be mocked, <hi>non verbis paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia agenda, ſed actu:</hi> let us not promiſe God better obedience with our lips, then we perform with our hearts. Be not raſh to vow a thing before <hi>God,</hi> but when thy word hath paſt thy lips, then be as carefull to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, as thou waſt forward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to promiſe.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, let us alwaies follow that holy counſell given in <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticus, In all thy actions think upon thy latter end, and thou ſhalt never doe amiſſe:</hi> and that of the Prophet <hi>David, keep innocency, and doe the thing that is right; for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49814:51"/>that ſhall bring a man peace at the last:</hi> peace with <hi>God,</hi> peace with men, and peace with our own conſcience. In the world, ſaith our <hi>Saviour,</hi> ſhall ye have trouble, but in me ye ſhall have peace. The world is our ſea, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> is our haven; the world is our warfare, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> is our reſt: the world is full of ſtorms, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> is our peace; in me you ſhall have peace. Hence it was, that the Saints of <hi>God</hi> alwayes have taken exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joy in their tribulation; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt was their comfort and peace: he ſweetned all their ſorrows.<note place="margin">Solus is charum non amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit, cui il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le charus eſt qui non amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur.</note> Hence it was that Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſo reſolutely brake forth; <hi>Hic ure, hic ſeca, modo in aeternum parcas;</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not what preſſures God laid upon him: So he vouchſafed patience here, and heaven here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49814:52"/>What ever we doe or can ſuffer in this life, the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of our eternall joy, ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely recompenſe the vveight of our ſorrovves: Our light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, vvhich are but fora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moment, doe cauſe unto us a farre more excellent and exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weight of glory. Our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat here is ſhort, but our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph eternall. And who would not endure a few croſſes and windings in his way, when he knowes they will bring him to his journeys end? Who would not, for a little ſeaſon, expoſe himſelf to the mercy of the waves,<note place="margin">Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile eſt, ut in utro<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſeculo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atus ſis, ut in caelo &amp; in terra appareas glorioſus. <hi>Hier.</hi>
                     </note> to be toſſed on the Sea, when he is aſſured, with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> to come ſafely to the ſhore?</p>
                  <p>Beſides we muſt not expect to eſtabliſh our happineſſe here, and to enjoy our heaven hereafter.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49814:52"/>It is impoſſible a man ſhould flow in his delights in this world; and then drink at the fountain of everlaſting bliſſe in the world to come.</p>
                  <p>O then let us embrace the conflict, that we may obtain the Crown. <hi>Melior eſt modica amaritudo in faucibus, quàm ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum tormentum in viſceribus: i. e.</hi> a little gall in the mouth is not ſo painfull, as continuall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the bowels. Farre better it is to ſumme up our reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onings here, then to have our debts upon the ſcore hereafter;<note n="*" place="margin">Vna ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra erit gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior in paena, quam cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum anni in ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſima paeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. <hi>Thomas de Kemp.</hi>
                     </note> farre better to unlooſe our ſouls, from the immoderate em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracements of the comforts of this world, and to endure the ſtraits &amp; pinchings of a more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved courſe for ſixty or ſeventy years in this life, then be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally tormented for ever more.</p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:49814:53"/>
                  <p>Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> hath an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent expreſſion to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Suppoſe a man, ſaith he, much deſiring ſleep, and in his perfect minde, had an offer made him of one nights ſweet reſt, upon condition to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed a hundred years for it: would he accept (think you) of his ſleep upon ſuch termes? Now look what one night is to an hundred years, the ſame is the life preſent, compared with that to come: Nay look what a drop of water is to the ſea; the ſame, and no more is a thouſand years to Eternity. Who then of ſound judgement, for the ſhort fruition of a tranſitory con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment in this life, would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf to the horror of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall flames in the life to come? And therefore whiles we have our abode in this vale
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49814:53"/>of miſery, we ſhould alwaies pray with Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> grant us, <hi>Lord,</hi> that we may ſo partake of temporall felicities, that we may not loſe eternall. All things under the Sunne have their alterations and changings, but things above are permanent, and of an induring ſubſtance. He that can be ſecure, and ſure of the happineſſe to come, builds up his houſe upon a firm foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. How ſmall a modell of time, how ſhort a period is the longeſt life, when once it is finiſhed? Recollect with thy ſelf, ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the years that are paſſed from <hi>Adams</hi> time untill now; turne over the whole Scripture, and the time ſince the fall will ſeem but as yeſterday. For what are the times paſt? If thou hadſt lived from <hi>Adams</hi> day till this hour;<note n="*" place="margin">Da, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, ut ſic poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deamus tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, ut non perdamus aeterna. Omnia ei ſalva ſunt, cui ſalva eſt beara a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitas.</note>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:49814:54"/>thou wouldſt eaſily have jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that this life hath no perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity in it, which flees away ſo ſwiftly. For what is the life of any man, ſuppoſe the longeſt age? It is but like the morning dew, like the twinkling of an eye, in a trice it is gon. I have ſeen an end of all perfection, ſaith <hi>David.</hi> But here, ô Chriſtian, let me deal more plainly with thee; thou wilt readily acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge all things under the frame of Heaven are periſhing, and Heaven is thy thought, Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is thine aym. Now if it be ſo, why art thou then ſo dul in thy courſe of holineſſe, ſo fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen in thy zeal, ſo inclinable to every motion of ſin, ſo eaſily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by every incitement to wantonneſſe, never more calm and unſeaſonably patient, then when thy affections ſhould be
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49814:54"/>enflamed, and thy heart kindled with a juſt indignation in Gods cauſe? and on the other ſide, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more fretting, whining and unquiet, then when thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be meek &amp; patient, &amp; cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſpoſed under the burden of afflictions? How can it be that we ſhould have eternity in our mindes, &amp; yet live no better in our manners? Now that we may the eaſier diſcern the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulnes of our hearts herein; let us examine our ſelves by the example of <hi>Iacob.</hi> This <hi>Patriarch Iacob</hi> ſerved his uncle <hi>Laban</hi> ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years for <hi>Rachel</hi> his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the greatnes of his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction towards her, made that time ſeem but as a few dayes. (To apply this:) Thou art a Servant, as <hi>Iacob</hi> was, but thou ſerves not ſuch a Maſter as <hi>Iacob</hi> did, thou ſerves not man, but
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49814:55"/>God, thy maker and a faithfull rewarder; thou ſerves not for a wife, but for a kingdom; not for an earthly contentation, but for an heavenly habitation: And yet behold the ſhort affliction of one day can enervate thy love, and unlock thy affections from God and heaven: Every croſſe accident ſtops thee in thy courſe, every little ſorrow diſquiets thy ſoul, and leſſens thy content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Behold here, meaſure by the example of <hi>Iacob</hi> the ſtrength of thy love: <hi>Iacob</hi> could ſerve ſeaven years with chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes for a wife; but thou canſt hardly ſerve thy <hi>God</hi> ſo many dayes with a true affection for Heaven: For reckon up all the nights thou haſt: ſpent in prayer, ſumme up all the dayes that thou haſt worne out in religious exerciſes, and canſt thou then
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49814:55"/>truly ſay to <hi>God</hi> as <hi>Iacob</hi> did to his uncle, In thy ſervice night and day have I macerated my body with heat and cold, and my ſleep departed from mine eyes; twenty years have I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in thy ſervice: couldſt thou ſay thus, and ſay it truly, ô then what would be the end of thy labour, what would thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward be? not flocks of cattell, not the daughters of <hi>Laban,</hi> but God himſelf would be thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great reward, thy life and happines; He would be unto thee every thing that thy heart can deſire or long for; Thy ſoul ſhould flowe, and even melt in abundance of ſpirituall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</p>
                  <p>But now take a little view of thine own vilenes, thy own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, thy utter diſability to any thing that may be truly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49814:56"/>good. Thy hands are fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Gods work, thy feet are ſlow to Gods temple, thine eyes are ſeared, or ſhut up towards heaven; But for the works of fleſh and Satan, thy heart is hot to envy, thy minde prone to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, thy tongue voluble to blaſpheme, thy affections even glued and incorporated, as it were, into ſenſuall embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; And is this to ſerve God for Heaven? ſhall the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Saints,</hi> and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Angels,</hi> and the joy, and fruition of <hi>God</hi> himſelf, be pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out upon ſuch works as theſe? Doſt thou thus requite thy maker?</p>
                  <p>O conſider, conſider, I ſay, thy waies in time; labour to ſerve <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Iacob</hi> did: labour to approve thy ſelf as faithfull to <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Iacob</hi> was to his uncle
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49814:56"/>
                     <hi>Laban:</hi> And if the weight of the labour diſcourage thee, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity oppreſſe thee, or proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſeduce thee; then lift up thine eyes to heaven, as <hi>Iacob</hi> did to his <hi>Rachel:</hi> Let heaven be thy love, thy ſpouſe, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of thine eyes, the joy of thy heart; Behold, thy <hi>Rachel</hi> is fair, and lovely, Heaven is both beautifull and glorious: Let thy deſires goe before, whither thou meaneſt to haſten after: ſuffer for a ſeaſon thy light affliction, having an eye to the recompence of reward; yet and but a little while, and thou ſhalt approach the haven, where thou ſhalt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy ſo much the more happines,<note place="margin">Eo diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendus eſt ſpiritus, quo ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando eſt iturus.</note> by how much the deeper thou haſt drunk in ſorrow; and by how much the more ardent thy affections have been towards <hi>God</hi> in this life, the more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49814:57"/>ſhall thy reward be in the life to come; then ſhall thy croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes prove thy gains, and that well-ſpring of joy which ſhall ever riſe in thy heart, ſhall ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low up all thy ſorrows.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Shewing that there is no other way, nor poſsible means to attain to the true eternity, but by a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent affiance upon the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SUch and ſo deplorable is the condition of every man, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in his corrupted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated ſtate, that albeit he be able by that ſmall ſpark of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall illumination, which is left in his minde, to ſee as in a glaſſe, darkly and obſcurely an eternity to come; yet is he utterly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49814:57"/>of the true way thereunto, neither hath he any poſſibility in nature to finde it out: He is in no better ſtate then the poor cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at the pool of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> who ſaw the waters that could heal him before his eyes, but found no means to help him into them. For that ſound and perfect knowledge of the true way, which man was adorned with in his firſt creation, is wholly loſt and extinguiſhed in him, he is now a meer <hi>stranger from the life of God,</hi> Epheſ. 4.18. <hi>dead in treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſses and ſinnes,</hi> Epheſ. 1.2. <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate to every good work,</hi> Tit. 1.16. <hi>his very minde is defiled,</hi> Tit. 1.15. <hi>his wiſdom is death,</hi> Rom. 8.6.<note n="*" place="margin">Nemo aliunde Deo pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, niſi ex eo quod ipſe dona. verit.</note> He is no more able of himſelf to leade a holy life, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, then a dead man is to perform the actions of one that is alive. Being thus
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49814:58"/>diſrobed of all ſpirituall endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſaving grace: how ſhall he attain to that joyfull <hi>Eternity,</hi> which his ſoul (as I have ſaid) may long for, but can no way reach? Certainly, there is no light to lead him, but that<note n="*" place="margin">Si Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem per Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum in te habes. <hi>Alſt.</hi>
                     </note> light of the world; no way for him to take to, but that <hi>new and living way, even him,</hi> who hath ſtiled himſelf, <hi>the way, the truth, and the life;</hi> no rock to cleave to, but this <hi>strong founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> no name under Heaven to be ſaved by, but this, even this alone, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt, yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever.</hi> He, and he alone is the onely ſure, effectuall, infallible means of our ſalvation: He alone is the true <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> who was once offered to take away ſinnes, and after that entered into the true <hi>ſanctuary,</hi> the very <hi>Heaven,</hi> to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49814:58"/>appear in the fight of God for us, where <hi>he is able perfectly to ſave them, which come unto God by him, ſeeing he ever liveth to make interceſsion for them.</hi> Heb. 7.26. He alone is the ground of our hope, the crown of our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the ſtrength of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.<note n="*" place="margin">Oculum tuum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine non excludit cor clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, nec manum tuam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellit du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritia homi. num. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                     </note> It's he alone, who by the ſweet influence of his grace, and by the ſecret working of his ſpirit, can (when he will,) and doth (when he pleaſe) ſubdue and bring under the moſt obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, gainſaying, and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious heart, to a cheerfull, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and ready obedience to his heavenly will. O the infinite and inexpreſſible tenderneſſe of our loving Saviour to wards us! When we, like ſheep, had gon aſtray, his mercy reduced us: When we lay wallowing in our blood, his pity refreſht us:
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49814:59"/>When we were dead in our ſins, his death did revive us: and here we may truly ſay with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, his mercy reacheth to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</hi> From the Heavens came the price of our redemption. We were not, neither could we be redeemed by the blood of bulls and goats, by thouſands of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of oyl, by the cattle that are upon a thouſand mountains. It was not the treaſures of the world, the power of men or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels could purchaſe this free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, nothing could cleanſe us, but the blood of the <hi>Lamb:</hi> He was that fountain, opened for ſin, and for uncleanneſſe; He was that <hi>Sonne of righteouſnes,</hi> that came with healing in his wings. His were the wounds, that healed our ſores; his was the back, that bare our ſorrows; his was the price, that quit our
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49814:59"/>ſcores; he aſſumed our fleſh to redeem us here, and he reigns as a king to crown us hereafter. Now what remains after all this to be done on our parts? Let us reſt on this <hi>Anchor,</hi> let us flee to this <hi>hold,</hi> and build on this <hi>foundation: For no other founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can any man lay, then that which is laid, Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Let us caſt our ſouls into the arms of our <hi>Saviour: In brachijs Salvato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris mei &amp; vivere vole, &amp; mori eupio,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard:</hi> O let this be our deſire: Now the gate is open, let us not deferre the time of entrance: Now is the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable time, let us not procra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate the ſeaſon: Now he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers his mercy, he ſhews his long ſufferance, let us not turn his grace into wantonneſſe; let us follow the counſell of the ſonne of <hi>Sirach:</hi> Eccleſ. the 5. <hi>Make
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49814:60"/>no long tarrying to turn to the Lord,</hi> and put not off from day to day: For ſuddainly ſhall the wrath of the Lord break forth, and in thy ſecurity thou ſhalt be deſtroyed, and thou ſhalt periſh in time of vengeance. But alas, farre otherwiſe it is with us in our practice:<note n="*" place="margin">Magna pars vitae elabitur male agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, maxima nihil age<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, tota aliud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentibus.</note> A great portion of our time is crumbled away in doing ill, a greater part in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing, and our whole life in doing that which we ſhould not, or in matters (as we ſay) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the by. And as <hi>Archime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> was ſecure and buſy about drawing lines on the ground, when <hi>Syracuſe</hi> was taken: ſo is it with us. Now that our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſafety lyes at ſtake, we lye puzling in our duſt, I mean, in our worldly negotiations: But for our eternity ſhortly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, we ſeldom or rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49814:60"/>think of it. We are, like <hi>Martha,</hi> trouble about ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, when one thing is neceſſary: But this one thing is that, which of all other things is leaſt regarded, and in the laſt place. We ſeldom ſeek heaven, till death doth ſummon us to leave the earth: we have many evaſions to gull our own hearts, many excuſes to procra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate our repentance; like <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi> the <hi>Sicilian</hi> king, who to excuſe himſelf for the preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of the golden garment, which he took from his <hi>god A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo,</hi> anſwered, that ſuch a robe as that was, could not be at any ſeaſon of the year uſefull to his god: it would not keep him warm in the winter, and it was too heavy for the ſummer: So many there be, ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who play with God, and with
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49814:61"/>their own ſoul. You muſt not (ſay they) ſeek for the vigour and life of Religion in the hearts of young men; For youth, as the proverb is, muſt have his ſwinge: neither can you expect it in the company of the aged: for their age, and thoſe diſtempers, which accompany it, make them a burden to themſelves, and dulls the edge of their intentions unto all their ſerious undertakings. Thus both the ſummer and the winter of our age are unfit for Gods ſervice: But let us not thus cheat ourſelves. If God be God, let us follow him; let us not put off the day of reconciliation, and ſay in our hearts, To morrow we will do it, when yet we cannot tell, vvhat ſhall be to morrovv: for vvhat is our life? It is even a vapour, that appears for a little time, and afterwards vaniſheth
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49814:61"/>away. Hence it was that <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> being invited a day before to a feaſt, replyed to the meſſenger, Why doth thy Maſter invite me for to morrow, whereas for this many years I have not promiſed to my ſelf one daies life?<note place="margin">Nemo mortem ſatis ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet, niſi qui ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cavet.</note> No man dreads death as he ought, but he that alwaies expects his ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; and therefore we may truly judge ſuch men wofully ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and wilfull contemners of the future good, who can go to their beds, and reſt on their pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the apprehenſion of their known ſins, without a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar humiliation for them. For how oft doth a ſudden and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected death arreſt men? We ſee and know in our daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, many lay themſelves to ſleep in health and ſafety, yet are they found dead in the morning. Thus ſuddenly are they rapt
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49814:62"/>from their quiet repoſe to their irrecoverable judgement, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance from their feathers to flames of fire; ſuch is the frail condition of our brittle lives, vvithin the ſmall particle of an hour, live, and ſicken, and die: yet ſo groſſe is our blindneſſe, that from one day to another, nay, from one yeer to another, we triflingly put off the reformation of our lives, untill our laſt hour creepes on us unlookt for, and dragges us to eternitie.</p>
                  <p>Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> ſtriving with all his endeavours againſt the backwardnes and ſlownes of his own heart to turne to the Lord, bitterly complained within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Quamdiu, quamdiu, cras, cras? Quare non hâc horâ finis turpitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis meae?</hi> How long (ſaith he) ô how long ſhall I delude my ſoule with to morrows repentance?
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49814:62"/>Why ſhould not this hour ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate my ſinfulneſſe? We are every minute at the brink of death, &amp; every hour, that we paſſe thorow, might prove (for ought we know) the evening of our whole life, and the very cloſe of our mortalitie. Now if it ſhould pleaſe God to take away our ſouls from us this night (as ſuddenly falls out to ſome) what would then become of us? In what Eternitie ſhould we be found? Whether amongſt the damned, or the bleſſed? Happie were it for us, if we were but as carefull for the welfare of our ſouls, as we are curious for the adorning of our bodies: if our clothes or faces do contract any blot or ſoiling, we preſently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to cleanſe the ſame: But though our ſouls lie inthralled in the pollutions of ſin, this alas we
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49814:63"/>feel not; it neither provokes us to ſhame, nor moves us to ſorrow. Wherfore let us look into our hearts with a ſeverer eye: Let the ſhortneſſe of our dayes ſtir us up to theamendment of our ſinful lives; and let the hour, wherein we have ſinned, be the beginning of our reformation, according to that of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Agenda eſt paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolum ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licirè, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumetiam maturè.</note> Our <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance muſt be, not onely ſincere, but timely alſo: whileſt we have the light, let us walk as children of the light:</hi> Let us not any longer cheat our ſouls in ſtudying to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent evaſions or pretences for our ſins; but rather lay open our ſores, and ſeek to the true <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> that can heal them. All the creatures under the ſun do natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally intend their own preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and deſire that happineſſe, which is agreeable to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: onely man is negligent, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:49814:63"/>impiouſly careleſſe of his own welfare. We ſee the Hart, when he is ſtriken and wounded, looks ſpeedily for a certain herb, well known unto him by a kinde of naturall inſtinct; &amp; when he hath found it, applies it to the wound. The ſwallow, when her young ones are blinde, knowes how to procure them their ſight by the uſe of her Celandine: But we alas are wounded, yet ſeek for no remedy; we go cuſtomarily to our beds, to our tables, to our good company; but who is he that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves his conſtant courſe of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, of repentance, of hearty and ſincere humiliation for his ſins? We go forward ſtill in our old way, and jogge on in the ſame rode: Though our judgement ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten, hell threaten, death ſtand ar the door, yet we thruſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtill; <hi>&amp; in dulcem declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namus
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49814:64"/>lumina ſomnum:</hi> But alas, miſerable ſouls as we are, can we embrace quiet reſts and uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted ſleeps with ſuch wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed conſciences? Can we be ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, being ſo near our ruine?</p>
                  <p>But you will ſay, we have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed already many nights without danger; no ſickneſſe in the night hath befalne us hitherto, why then ſhould any fear of death amaze or trouble us?</p>
                  <p>Admit all this, yet, be not too confident; one hour may accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh that, which a thouſand years could not produce: and think with your ſelves, what a little diſtance there is, between your ſouls and death: Let me ask the ſtrongeſt of men on earth, what certainty of life canſt thou promiſe thy ſelf, ſeeing that either a little bone in thy throat may choak thee, or a tile from
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49814:64"/>thy houſe may brain thee, or ſome malignant ayre may poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thee,<note place="margin">Tu te pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptum miraberis, quam me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tueres ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</note> and then where art thou? There are a thouſand waies, whereby ſuddenly a man may come to his end; and certain it is, that <hi>Mors illa maxime impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſa eſt, cujus vita praecedens non fuit provida, i.e.</hi> that death is the ſuddeneſt, which is not uſhered in with a foregoing preparation. It is therefore a ſpeciall point of wiſdom to think every day our laſt, yea to account every hour the period of our lives. For look how many pores there are in the bodie, ſo many windows are there to let in death: yea, we car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry our deaths continually about us in our boſomes; and who can promiſe himſelf his life till the evening? Death doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſend forth her harbingers to give notice of her coming; ſhe
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49814:65"/>often preſſeth in unlookt for, and ſuddenly attacheth the unprovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſoul. Watch therefore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye know neither the day, not the hour: work whileſt ye have the day; for the night comes, wherein no man can work: look towards thy evening, and caſt thy thoughts upon that long Eternitie; Death firſt or laſt will apprehend thee: expect it therefore at every turn, and of this aſſure thy ſelf,<note n="*" place="margin">Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alis quiſque in hac vita moritur, talis in die noviſſimo judicabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> as death lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth thee, ſo ſhal judgement finde thee. How improvidently ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure then are thoſe, who ſet up their reſt in the comforts of this life, and overly-regard their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall welfare? This is the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall careleſneſſe of our times.</p>
                  <p>If a man have a perpetuitie but of five ſhillings yearly rent, what travel, and pains, and ſweat, what beating of his braine and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49814:65"/>exhauſting of his treaſure wil he run thorow, before he will loſe one dram of his right? Yet our eternall inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is caſt behinde us, &amp; undervalued as a trifle, not worth the ſeeking, &amp; this ſhews our ſmall love to our home: for we little eſteem of that which we take ſmall pains for. All other things, which conduce to our temporall well being, we ſeek with circumſpection, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them with content, but matters of <hi>Eternitie</hi> we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of, as things far diſtant from us, we ſcarcely entertain them in our thoughts. We buſie not our underſtandings in the ſearch of thoſe things which we ſee not: things preſent &amp; obvious to our ſight do beſt affect us. We are ill ſighted upward, weak and dim eyes have we towards heaven.</p>
                  <p>The truth of this appeares even in children, who preſently
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:49814:66"/>even from the cradle, drink in the rudiments of vice; they learn to ſwear, riot, drink, and the like enormities with the ſmalleſt teaching; but they are utterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed to any vertuous inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. They ſoon apprehend what belongs to the curioſitie of behaviour, and deportment of the body, and the faſhions of the times; <hi>Hoc diſcunt omnes ante Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha &amp; Beta puelli;</hi> but for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and that Eternity, they are wholly averſe from it, they are utterly uncapable of the things above; they carry about them, as the liverie of their firſt parents, not only an indiſpoſition, but a very oppoſition to goodneſſe: And whereas for other imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and undertakings, they have certain naturall notions in them, bending their intentions to naturall works, ſome one way, and ſome another; yet they have
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49814:66"/>not ſo much as any apprehenſion of the things of God.<note n="*" place="margin">Homo ſine gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia praeter carnem nihil ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligit aut poteſt.</note> Thus it is with children, and thus it is with all men, even thoſe of the ripeſt, and moſt piercing under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, untill the light of <hi>Gods</hi> Spirit hath ſhined on the hearts, and powerfully wrought ſome ſpirituall holy diſpoſitions in in them. <hi>The naturall man</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>neither doth, nor can diſcern the things that are of God.</hi> O how infinitely miſerable and deplorable is his ſtate, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving neither knowledge of the true life, nor poſſibilitie of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to finde it out:<note n="*" place="margin">Cum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ul ſit a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat in via.</note> yet runnes on ſecurely in his damned way, untill he fall wofully and irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verably into the pit, wher he will not have, (no not when he hath uncomfortably worne out mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of years) the leaſt intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſorrow, or drop of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49814:67"/>or hope of pardon? Here on earth malefactors condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to die, have this comfort (though wretched) that one hour commonly terminates all their griefes in this life: but the torments of the damned are not concluded in an age; nay, the end and period of ten thouſand yeers will not end their ſorrow: And this is it which adds more to their ſufferings, even their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie knowledge of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuitie of them; they have not ſo much as any hope of releaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>Hope in this life hath ſuch a power in it, that it can yeeld ſome comfort in the middeſt of trouble; the ſick man, whileſt his ſoul is in him, he hath hope, but after this life, this ſmall refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is denied the damned, all their hope is turned into deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:49814:67"/>The prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> cap. 4.14. heard the voice of an holy one crying, <hi>Hew down the tree, and cut off his branches, ſhake off his leaves, and ſcatter his fruit, nevertheles leave the ſtump of his root in the earth.</hi> Thus it is with men in this world, ſaith <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> their leaves and their flowers are ſhaken; their delights are taken from them; but the roots remain, and their hope is not aboliſhed. But it is not ſo in hell; (ſaith he) There both flower &amp; ſtump; nay, &amp; even all hope too, are baniſhed away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. The day of the <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaith the prophet <hi>Malachi,</hi> ſhall burn them up, &amp; leave them neither root nor bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch. The very hope, ſaith <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> of the wicked ſhal periſh; what ſhould this teach us, but whilſt our hope remains, to improve our few daies to our beſt adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, to make ſtraighter paths
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:49814:68"/>to our ſelves, to abridge our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate appetites, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their vain and fruitleſſe joyes; and with all the power of our affections ſtrive to attain that haven, where no billow ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright us, no ſtorms aſtoniſh us, no perils indanger us? Then ſhall our diſſolution prove our gain, and our death our glory: if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we perſiſt wilfully in the paths of our voluptuouſnes, and ſolace our ſelves in the vain ioyes of our own hearts, &amp; in the ſight of our eyes; certainly it will be bitternes in the later end.<note n="*" place="margin">Ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ema gaudii lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pat.</note> All our earthly delights will glide away lik a ſwift river: <hi>The rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the wicked is ſhort,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob, and the joy of a ſinner is but for a moment:</hi> Though his excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie mount up to the heaven, and his head reach unto the clouds, yet ſhall he periſh for ever like his
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:49814:68"/>dung, but the righteous is like a ſtrong mountain, and he ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore to draw to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, juſt occaſion might here be taken for deploring the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and unhappy condition of our times. Where are there any that take into their thoughts the due conſideration of the time to come?<note place="margin">Sic pleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que vivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ac ſi f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet omni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> aeternitas.</note> Where ſhall we finde any truly provident for immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality? we ſo live as though we conceived of Eternity but as of a fable, or a dream; the ſweet allurements of ſin doe ſo ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beguile many, that by gentle degrees they obliterate, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh in them all love of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and the very inclinations themſelves to any thing, that may be truly tearmed good.</p>
                  <p>But let us no longer delude our ſelves, by fancying a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49814:69"/>on earth, behold the judge ſtands before the door:<note n="*" place="margin">Mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fiet, quod tota doleat ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitas. Ante ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los prae omnibus habeamus diem ul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> mum, &amp; momentis ſingulis ſupplicia timeamus dolorum aeternoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> The ſtrongeſt holds in the World will not be able to detain us one minute, when God ſhall be pleaſed to call for our ſouls: and therefore let us, before all things, have continually in our ſight the laſt day: and let us every moment fear the puniſhment of eternall pains.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Certain concluſions drawn from the ſerious and devout conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Eternity.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label>The firſt concluſion.</label>IF they, who runne on in any notorious ſin,<note place="margin">Confecto demum ſcelere, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligitur.</note> did but rightly weigh how faſt they goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Eternity of torments, (ſince that by the leaſt command or ſtroke of God, they may be
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:49814:69"/>unavoidably hurl'd to death and deſtruction:) Certainly they would not, for all the kingdomes in <hi>Europe,</hi> for all the treaſures of <hi>Aſia,</hi> nay not for the whole world, deferre their repentance one houre; much leſſe would they goe ſo confidently to their beds, without fear or horrour, being ſo near the pits brink, and lying in the danger of ſo great a ſin: For what would it profit a man, to winne the whole world, and loſe his ſoul? wherefore who ever thou art, <hi>Nulli parcas, ut ſoli parcas animae,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Omnia ſi perdas animam ſervare memento:</note> what ever become of all other things, yet have a ſpeciall care for the ſalvation of thy precious ſoul.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. Our heads are fild with care in theſe ſtrait and pinching times, how we ſhall live in the world, when our ſouls ſhould
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:49814:70"/>be more inquiſitive? how we ſhall live out of the world, when death hath landed us in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. For what matters it, how ſhort our ſtock of proviſions be here, where we are breaking up houſe, and on the point of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting? A man that comes to an Inne, if he meet with hard fare, courſe lodging, it never troubles him: for it is, ſayes he, but for a night, I ſhall away next morrow; ſo our habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this world, are but like <hi>Jonahs</hi> gourd, they ſhelter us but (as it were) for a night; I care not formans day (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) and in truth wherein is it to be regarded? for what is mans day to eternity? What is it to that God with whom we muſt live for ever? Therefore care we not whether our ſailes be high or low, or what vain men
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:49814:70"/>think of us, but what the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>God</hi> thinks of us: and what we ſhall be thought of in that Kingdom, where we muſt live and abide for ever.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. Did faith give men as cleer a ſight of ſpirituall things, as ſenſe doth of temporall, what manner of lives would they live? how would they be exalted in the world above the world? I have loſt, ſaies one, the favour of ſuch and ſuch great men: but is there not ten thouſand times more ſweetnes in the favour of <hi>God?</hi> Theſe ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing times, ſaith another, have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved me of wife, children, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, what ever was neer and dear unto me; well, but is not the Author of all thy comfort alive ſtill? and will not the light of the fun content thee, though all thy candles be put out? cheer
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:49814:71"/>up, man, bare Chriſt is wealth enough; if <hi>God</hi> be thy portion, thou injoyeſt infinitely more, then the world can lend thee: For all creature-comforts have but their meaſure, and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of goodnes in them: no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath all good in it; Cloaths ſerve but to warm us, meat to nouriſh us, houſes to ſhelter us, phyſick to recover us, but <hi>God</hi> hath all good in himſelf: he is ſight to the blinde, health to the ſick, liberty to the captive, light to them that ſit in darknes, all things to all men. They that put their truſt in the <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Shall want no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of thing that is good.</hi> This is very full, <hi>no manner of thing that is good:</hi> mark what <hi>God</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abraham, I am thy exceeding great reward; God</hi> is a reward, an exceeding great reward to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:49814:71"/>his people; when you take in any creature comfort, you doe but ſip at <hi>Gods</hi> bounty: but when you taſte of <hi>God himſelf,</hi> oh then you have a fulnes indeed. <hi>In thy preſence is fulnes of joy, and at thy right hand, there is pleaſure for evermore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">IV. We carry immortall ſouls about us, and therefore we ſhould have immortall aims, immortall ends. When Satan ſhall tender any thing as lovely to thy apprehenſion, ſay to him, will thy pleaſure, thy ſecurity, thy eaſe, to which thou inviteſt my ſoul, abide for ever? I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be happy but in an eternall good. That which muſt fill up all the chinks of my ſoul, muſt be a pure good, a totall good, and an eternall good. If the good I doe injoy, be not pure and all good, then ſome thing
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:49814:72"/>muſt be wanting, and there will be imperfection: and though it be pure and all good, yet if not unchangeably ſo, then it is but like a candle, which at laſt will be extinguiſhed: and the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration that it muſt end, will diminiſh my happines, and abate my joy. But ſure I am, my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours counſell is ſweet and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and incloſeth fulnes of comfort in it; <hi>Labour not for the meat which periſheth, but for that which endureth to eternall life.</hi> Since a portion may be had in dyamonds, why ſhould I ſet my heart on lumber?</p>
                  <p n="5">V. Some begin to live, when they are about to dye, and this eſtate is perillous: and ſome doe dye before they beginne to live, and this eſtate is deſperate; the ſpeedieſt work is ſafeſt, when thou tradeſt for eternity. Too
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:49814:72"/>late providence is often ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with everlaſting repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Many there are,<note place="margin">Caeſi ad aeternita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, ex qua nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt.</note> who runne headlong, and blindfold to their long home, like the rich glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in rhe Goſpell, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver began to open his eyes and look upwards, till he was in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: All the while he lived on earth, his eyes were ſhut up, and when it was too late, namely when he was thrown to hell, then began he to look upward and about him.</p>
                  <p>So many now adaies they goe on in a pleaſing and eaſie way; And<note n="*" place="margin">In via nemo er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, ſed in fine viae, via pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus placet, ſed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicet &amp; terret viae t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rminus.</note> they are never ſenſible that they are out of the way, till they arrive at the end of their journey. All the miſery lies in the cloſe of the day, For out of the pit is no redemption: when once the ſoul is ſplit upon this
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:49814:73"/>rock, it gives to the world his everlaſting farewell, according to that of <hi>Job.</hi> cap. 7.9. <hi>as the cloud vaniſheth and goeth away; ſo he that goes down to the grave, ſhall come up no more, he ſhall return no more to his houſe, neither ſhall his place know him any more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">VII. It is recorded of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> that after his reſurrection from the dead, he was never ſeen to laught; The ſtream of his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were now turned into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chanell; his thoughts were fixt in heaven, though his body was on earth: and therefore<note n="*" place="margin">Aeternis inhianti in faſtidio ſunt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toria, <hi>Bern.</hi>
                     </note> he could not but ſlight tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things, when his heart was bent towards eternall. Oh, that we could work our hearts and ſouls to a vehement thirſt after <hi>Christ,</hi> the true eternity! For if <hi>Chriſt</hi> be our end, our joy ſhall be endleſſe, <hi>nullo fine regna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:49814:73"/>cum Chriſto, ſi Chriſtus tibi finis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. The minde of man is ſo much the more ſenſible of the evil preſent, by how much leſſe it meditates on the good to come. For he that looks to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the reward, will vilify the ſufferings. Saint <hi>Austin</hi> runs on ſweetly in his meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon this ſubject; Eternall labour, ſaith he, is but an equall compenſation for an eternall reſt. But if thou ſhouldeſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure this eternall labour, thou couldſt never arrive at that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reſt: Therefore hath the mercy of God ordained thy ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows to be temporall, that thy joys may be eternall; and yet, ſaith he,<note n="*" place="margin">Ubi eſt cogitatio Dei? ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundae fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae ſunt cogitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Dei. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                     </note> who is there, that thinks on <hi>God</hi> as he ought? Such thoughts are irkſome to us; But for temporall vanities we think
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:49814:74"/>of them with delight; and enjoy them with contentment: Now, ſaith he, look in and about thy ſelf,<note place="margin">Noli gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere ut piſcis, qui in ſua ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultat eſca, nondum enim tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit hamum piſcator. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                     </note> ſee where thou art; <hi>God</hi> hath his hook in thy noſtrills, and can pluck thee up when he pleaſeth: and though he ſuffer thee (according to thy calculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) a long time, yet what is the longeſt time of man to eternity? Yea though thou ſhouldeſt lengthen out thy dayes to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred of years; yet ſtill thou art tranſitory, and expoſed to the common condition of all men. Then fix thy heart on <hi>God,</hi> and ſo enjoying that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, thou ſhalt make thy ſelf eternall; and be not diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for thy tribulations, and daily diſquietings in this world: for ſuch is gods love, ſuch his abundant kindnes towards his elect; that he<note n="*" place="margin">Ideo Deus ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renis faeli citatibus amaritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem miſcet, ut alia quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitas, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus dulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do non eſt fallax.</note> corrects them,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:49814:74"/>to the end they might not be condemned with the world hereafter. Be not therefore (I ſay) caſt down with any croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes whatſoever, that may befall thee in this life; for the things that are preſent, are temporall, but the things to come are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. When we ſee the friends of this world, the eager embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the comforts of this life, upon every ſummons of death ſtrive to deferre, what they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not utterly avoid, their corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſſolutions; oh how great care, what indefatigable dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, what reſtleſſe endeavours ſhould we uſe, that we might live for ever? Let us again, and again, meditate on theſe things, and with due care foreſee eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, before we unexpectedly fall into it. Certain it is,<note n="*" place="margin">Omnia tranſeunt, fola reſtat &amp; non tranſibit aeternitas.</note> all things paſſe away in this life, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:49814:75"/>eternity hath no period: let us redeem the time, and work while we have the day: for if we neglect good duties here, we ſhall never regain the like op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity hereafter. This life (ſaith <hi>Nazianzen</hi>) is as it were our <hi>fairday</hi> or market-day, let us now buy what we want, while the faire laſts; while we have time, let us doe good unto all men:<note n="*" place="margin">Tu dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis ſed tempus tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um non dormit, ſed ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat imo volat. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne illis qui ſic vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vunt, ſicut vixiſſe ſe volunt cum moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antque ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quae in ae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ternitate conſtituti feciſſe ſe gaudebu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Amb.</hi>
                     </note> Happy is the man that ſo lives here, that the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his well-ſpent life, may yeeld him joy hereafter; For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe <hi>levis hic neglectus, ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum fit diſpendium, i.e.</hi> A ſmall neglect in the ordering of our time in this world, will be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with an eternall loſſe in the world to come.</p>
                  <p n="9">IX. Death is the ending of our dayes, not of our life. For when our day ſhall cloſe, and our time
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:49814:75"/>ſhall be no more, then ſhall our death conduct us to a life, which will laſt for all Eternity: For we dye not here to dye, but to live for ever. Therefore the beſt guide of our life, is the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our death: and he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone leads a life anſwerable to his Chriſtian profeſſion, who daily expects to leave it. Me thinks 'its ſtrange, men ſhould be ſo induſtriouſly carefull to avoid their death, and ſo careleſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provident of the life to come, when as nothing makes death bad, but that eſtate which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows it: but the reaſon is, we are ſpiritually blinde and ſee not, nor know, in this our day, the things that belong to our peace. We have naturally neither ſight nor feeling of the joyes to come. But when God ſhall enlighten the darkneſſe of our mindes, and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:49814:76"/>reveal his ſonne in us, vvhen once the <hi>day dawneth,</hi> and that <hi>day-ſtarre</hi> ariſeth in our hearts, ô then our death will be our joy, and the rejoycing of our hearts, then ſhall we infinitely deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with <hi>Christ.</hi> Let us therefore with unwearied endeavours labour to bring <hi>Chriſt</hi> home to our hearts, and to keep him there. Let us dye to our ſelves, and to our luſts here, that ſo in the world to come, we may ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly live unto Chriſt and in him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>Some directions for the better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of our lives, in the way to a happy eternity.</head>
                  <p>SInne and grace are both eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, both reach to eternity; and ſo doe all the actions that
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:49814:76"/>proceed from either. Hence it follows, that a gracious life, is the beaten path-way to a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous eternity. Therefore to the end thy Being hereafter may be as happy, as it muſt be long: take in theſe directions.</p>
                  <p>In all thy dealings amongſt the ſonnes of men, be that thou ſeemeſt; amuſe not the world with flouriſhes, labour not to be more outwardly glorious, then inwardly ſincere. Alas, what a melancholy peece of buſines will it prove in the end, to be a man of praiſes, as it were, for a day: and afterwards (if repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance prevent it not,) to be a man of ſorrows for ever? to have this life comfortable, and eternity miſerable? What ever thy hand ſhall finde to be done, caſt firſt in thy thoughs: Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther durſt I act this ſame thing,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:49814:77"/>were I now to die?<note n="*" place="margin">Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid agis, quicquid ſuſcipis, tecum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us cogita, num tale aliquod ageres, ſi hac hora eſſet mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riendum.</note> Its good to live by dying principles. A frequent arraignment of thy heart, will render thy life com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, thy death peacefull, thy eternity glorious, and ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee from many ſnares and temptations, which otherwiſe ſin and Satan would caſt upon thee.</p>
                  <p>When thou ſetteſt upon any religious duty, ſeriouſly weigh with thy ſelf, what the temper of thy heart is towards it. Oh what a ſad thing is it, (if judiciouſly balanced,) to think I have begun, and ended a holy duty, before a moſt holy God, but felt not what I ſpake. My heart was ſealed up: labour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore above all things, whilſt thy ſoul in any exerciſe is in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, to keep thy affection on the wing, and ſtrive
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:49814:77"/>not ſo much to be long winded, as heart-wounded in thy petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as knowing aſſuredly, that when once thy devotion is flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, (though thy ſpeech doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue,) thy prayer is done.</p>
                  <p>We live in diſmall dayes, fire and ſword rage round about us, yet our greateſt enemies lodge in our boſome. Labour thou by thy prayers and pains to maſter thy corruptions: Then cruell cut throats, though they may pull thy heart from thy body, can never take God from thy heart, then death it ſelf, (that king of terrors) need not affright thee, becauſe hereby thy ſoul is but let out of a cage, and her out going from this life, is but an in going to a better.</p>
                  <p>When once thou haſt devoted thy ſelf to the ſervice of God, thou wilt finde thy heart to be a very buſy thing. Thou wilt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:49814:78"/>and anon be forcing thy ſelf upon vows and reſolution, to doe more for God, to fight more eagerly, more effectually againſt thy worſer ſelf; but remember this by the way, that ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence is an inlet to often fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; Therefore ingage <hi>Christ</hi> with thee, in all thy purpoſes: and let S. <hi>Pauls.</hi> profeſſion, in this particular, be thy inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and digeſt it into practice; I can doe all things through <hi>Chriſt</hi> that ſtrengthens me.</p>
                  <p>There is now adayes much wording of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world, but favour and frowns, like ſtrange byaſſes, doe frequently twiſt men round; and this is the garb of theſe unhappy times; but to avoid intanglements of this nature, <hi>study to be quiet, and meddle with thine own buſines:</hi> (and as it is ſaid of humble men,) be thou more troubled with thy
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:49814:78"/>ſelf, then with all the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. Live (as thou canſt,) a diſingaged man. <hi>Innocency, and Independency,</hi> are prevalent means to keep the ſoul cloſe to God.</p>
                  <p>I have done with directing thee: the Lord direct us all, that our reformation may be anſwerable to our incoms of mercy, otherwiſe, though all our enemies were deſtroyed, yet ſhall we finde diviſions enough at home to ruine us.</p>
                  <p n="10">X. Now that we may be the better incouraged to raiſe up our endeavours to the attainment of this happy eternity; Let us in a word conſider the abundant, and the ever-flowing happines in the world to come; Neither eye hath ſeen, nor eare hath heard, nor tongue can expreſſe the joys that <hi>God</hi> hath provided for them that love him. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> being raviſhed with the deſire of
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:49814:79"/>this life breaketh out with an inflamed affection:<note place="margin">U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum erit malum, nullum latebit bonum.</note> how great ſhall that happines be, where there can be no unclean thing, where no good can be wanting; where every creature doth praiſe and admire his <hi>Creatour,</hi> who is all in all things? How great ſhall that reward be,<note place="margin">Fraemiun virtutis critipſe, qui virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dedit.</note> where the river of vertue ſhall be himſelf the reward of vertue? how great ſhall that abundance be, where the author of all plenty ſhall be unto me life and ſoul, and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, health, and peace, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and all things; yea the end and compleat object of all my deſires? For in his preſence is the fulnes of joy, and at his right hand there is pleaſure for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. How great ſhall that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe be, where we ſhall have the Lord our debtor, who hath promiſed to reward our good deeds; where we ſhall have the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:49814:79"/>Lord for our portion, who will be to us, (as he was to <hi>Abraham</hi>) our exceeding great reward? How great ſhall that light be, where the Sunne ſhall no more ſhine by day, nor the moon by night; where <hi>God</hi> ſhall be our light, and the <hi>Lord</hi> our glory? How great ſhall that poſſeſſion be, where the heart ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe whatſoever it ſhall deſire, and ſhall never be deprived of its poſſeſſions? Here will be to the Saints an abundant, everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, overflowing banquet; no grief can accompany it, no ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſucceed it. Here is joy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſadneſſe, reſt<note n="*" place="margin">Quies motus no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appetitus.</note> without la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, wealth without loſſe, health without languor, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance without defect, life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out death, perpetuity without corruption. Here is the beatifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call preſence of God, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Saints, the ſociety of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:49814:80"/>Angels. Here are pleaſures, which the mindes of the behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers can never be wearied with; they alvvaies ſee them, and yet alwaies rejoyce to ſee them: Theſe are the flagons of wine, vvhich comforted up <hi>David,</hi> when he cried out, According to the multitude of the ſorrowes which I had in my heart, thy comforts have refreſhed my ſoul: <hi>In coelo eſt vita ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vitalis,</hi> In heaven, and onely in Heaven is the true life: For there our memories ſhal live in the joyfull recordation of all things paſt; our underſtandings ſhall live in the knowledge of God; our wills ſhall live in the fruition of all excellencies that they can wiſh for, all our ſenſes ſhall abound in their ſeverall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights. Here is that white ſtone, which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeakes of, even glory and immortality to them
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:49814:80"/>that overcome. Here is that <hi>water of life,</hi> which our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſpeakes of, whereof whoſoever drinks ſhall never thirſt again. Here is that river, the ſprings whereof make glad the hearts of men: And how earneſtly are we invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to theſe delights; come buy, wine and oil without money? Heaven is at ſale, and thou maiſt buy if thou wilt, and ſhrug not at the greatneſſe of the price, give but thy ſelf to God, and thou ſhalt have it. And who would not abandon his honours, his pride, his credit, his friends, nay himſelf? Who would not be willing to paſſe thorow the gates of hell, and endure infernall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for a ſeaſon, ſo he might be certain of ſo glorious and eternall an inheritance hereafter? Let all the devils in hell (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) beſet me round; let faſtings macerate my body;<note n="*" place="margin">Coelum venale eſt, nec mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum exae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtues pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter pretij magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> te ipſum da, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebis il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:49814:81"/>let ſorrows oppreſſe my minde;<note place="margin">Bone Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu qui par cendo ſae prus nos à te abijcis, feriendo effice ut ad te rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus <hi>Ger. med.</hi>
                     </note> let pains conſume my fleſh, let watchings dry me, or heat ſcorch me, or cold freeze and contract me; let all theſe, and what can come more, happen unto me, to I may enjoy my Saviour. For how excellent ſhall the glory of the juſt be? how great their joy, when every face ſhall ſhine as the ſun; when our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſhall martiall the Saints in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct orders, and ſhall render to every one according to his works? O were thy affections rightly ſetled on theſe heavenly manſions, how abject and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath thee wouldeſt thou eſteem thoſe things, which before thou ſetſt an high price upon? As he which aſcends an high mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ain, when he cometh to the top thereof, findes the middle ſteps low, and beneath him, which ſeemed to be high to him while
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:49814:81"/>he ſtood in the bottom; ſo he which ſends his thoughts to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, however he eſteemed of the vaniſhing pleaſures of the world, when his heart lay groveling on the earth below, now in this his tranſcendency he ſees them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, and viliſies them all in regard of heavenly treaſures. Let us therefore chearfully follow that advice of a reverend Father:<note n="*" place="margin">Quod a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquando per neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitatem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, pro ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te eſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</note> Let us here willingly part with that for heaven, which we muſt firſt or laſt neceſſarily leave upon earth, and let all the ſtrength of our ſtudies, and the very height of our endeavours be diſpended for the attainment of Eternitie. For certaine it is howſoever we live here like ſecure people of a ſecure age, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we waſte out the ſtrength and flower of our dayes, as if we ſhould never account for it; yet our judgement is moſt ſure;
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:49814:82"/>and ſhall not be avoided: The ſentence of the Judge will be one day moſt aſſuredly publiſhed, and ſhall not be revoked: <hi>We muſt all appear</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>before the judgement ſeat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad.</hi> Then ſhall our wickedneſſe be brought to light, which now lies hid in darknes. I <hi>ſaw the dead</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> Revel. 20.12.) <hi>both great and ſmall ſtand before God, and the books were opened, and another book was opened, which is the book of life, and the dead were judged of thoſe things which were written in the books, according to their works; and whoſoever was not found witten in the book of life, was caſt into the lake of fire.</hi> Thus it is evident, every man ſhall give up his account; every ſoul ſhall firſt or laſt come to his reckoning:
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:49814:82"/>
                     <hi>Multorum vocatio, paucorum ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio, omnium retributio;</hi> Many are called, few choſen, but all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded according to their deeds. Oh then let us prepare our ſelves to meet our God; let us come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him with fear, and tremble at his judgements. <hi>Fear not him,</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>who when he hath killed the body, can do no more, but fear him, who can caſt both ſoul and body to hell; I ſay, him fear.</hi> Oh hovv many of the Saints of God trembled and quaked, when they have meditated upon the laſt judgement? <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith, as oft as I think of that day, how doth my whole body quake, and my heart vvithin me tremble? <hi>Cyril</hi> ſaith, I am afraid of hell, becauſe the worme there dies not, and the fire never goeth out: I horribly tremble (ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>) at the teeth<note n="*" place="margin">A den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiae infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>: quis dabit oculis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is fontem lachryma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ut prç eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am fleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus fletu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſtrido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium?</note> of that infernall beaſt. Who will give to mine
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:49814:83"/>eyes (ſaith he) a fountain of tears, that by my weeping here I may prevent vveping and gnaſhing of teeth hereafter? And have the Saints of <hi>God</hi> thus ſhrunk at the thoughts of hell? hovv ſhould then the loyns of the vvicked quake and tremble?</p>
                  <p>Come novv thou prophane vvretch, of a prophane age, vvho at every vvord almoſt that drops from thy irreligious mouth, ſpeakeſt damnation to thy ſoul: bealching out ever and anon, theſe or the like execrable ſpeeches, Would I were damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if I knew this or that; God damne me body and ſoul, if I doe it not. Alas, alas, ſeemeth it a light thing in thine eyes, to play with flames, to ſport thy ſelf with everlaſting burnings? Tell mee, doſt thou know, or diddeſt thou ever caſt it in thy thoughts, what a condition it is
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:49814:83"/>to be damned? Hear a little and tremble; Thou ſhalt there, to thy greater horrour and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſee much joy, but never feel it: for thou ſhalt ſee <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and all the Prophets in the Kingdome of God, &amp; thou thy ſelf thruſt out, <hi>Luke.</hi> 6.13.28. As touching thy company: Though here on earth, thou wouldeſt not perchance be hired to lodge one night, in a houſe haunted with ſpirits, yet there thou muſt inhabite with unclean divels for evermore, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.41. And to conclude in this thy cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate thy heart and tongue ſhall be full of curſings and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies. Thou ſhalt blaſpheme the God of heaven, for thy pains and ſores, thou ſhalt curſe thoſe that were the means to bring thee thither; curſe the time that ever thou loſt ſo many
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:49814:84"/>golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opportunities of getting grace, that thou haſt heard ſo many ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and no whit bettered by them. Curſe thy ſelf, that ſlighteſt ſo many wholſom reproofs, which might have happily been improved to the ſaving of thy ſoul. Say now (deſperate fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſinner) canſt thou be content in the apprehenſion of theſe miſeries, to curſe thy ſelf again to the nethermoſt of hell? or on the contrary, doſt thou now begin to be aſhamed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in thy ſelf, and is thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence affrighted with the ugly face of thy ſins, and of thoſe bitter torments that abide them? Know then, thou haſt to deal with a <hi>God, who when thou art truly moved for thy ſins, an mourn for thy ſufferings,</hi> Jer. 31.20. Thou haſt to deal with a God, who will <hi>meet</hi> thee when thou approacheſt to him, <hi>if thou worke righteouſnes, and remember him in his way,</hi> Iſa. 64.5. <hi>Thou haſt to deal with a God, who doth account it his ſtrange work to puniſh,</hi> Iſa. 28.21. <hi>And he doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the children of men,</hi> Lam. 3.33. Yea, thou haſt to deal with a
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:49814:84"/>God, who hath graciouſly proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the whole world, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to ſhew mercy: <hi>yea, with his whole heart, and with his whole ſoul,</hi> Jer. 32.41. Oh then be wiſe now for thy ſoul in time, and think it a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that thou art yet on this ſide hell. And whatever thou judgeſt thy ſelf worthy to be condemned for, at that terrible barre, condemn thy ſelf for it before hand, that the Lord may ſay, I will not judge this man, becauſe he hath judged himſelf already. And be aſſured, where mans converſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, there Gods diſpleaſure makes its period.</p>
                  <p>Excellent is that advice of Saint <hi>Gregory,</hi> weigh (ſaith he) and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the errours of thy life, while thy time ſerves; Tremble at that ſtrict judgement to come, while thou haſt health, leſt thou hear that bitter ſentence, (<hi>Goe ye curſed</hi>) goe forth againſt thee, when it is too late. Did man know what time he ſhould leave the world, carnall wiſdom would prompt him, to proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his time, ſome to pleaſure, and ſome to repentance. But he that
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:49814:85"/>hath promiſed pardon to the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, hath not aſſured the ſinner of an houres life.<note place="margin">Culpam tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m (du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vacat) pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſu u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicij (du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>les) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreſce, ne tunc amaram ſententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>udias; cum nul lis fletib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> evadas.</note> Since therefore we can neither prevent, nor foreſee death, let us alwaies expect it, and provide for it. Let us dye to our ſinnes here, that we may live to Chriſt hereafter, and let us ſuffer with Chriſt in this world, that we may rejoyce and raign with him in the world to come. When we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part this life, we goe to an eternity, to an eternity, I ſay, which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver end, never, never, me thinks this word, never, hath a mountanious weight in it; to an eternity which maketh every good action infinitely better, and every evill action infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſe. Oh the unhappines &amp; ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting woe of thoſe men, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the ſmall and trifling things of this life, before the eternall weight of glory hereafter: who to enjoy the ſhort comfort of a miſerable life here, are content to loſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>God, and ſociety of Angels for ever hereafter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49814:85"/>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
